<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">12325619</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">13486</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-13486-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Computer aided greenness by design approach for resolving and quantifying Triamterene and Hydrochlorothiazide in pharmaceutical mixtures employing multiscale dynamics simulations</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Elsonbaty</surname><given-names>Ahmed</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Attala</surname><given-names>Khaled</given-names></name><address><email>Khaled-Attala@eru.edu.eg</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Darweish</surname><given-names>Eman</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/029me2q51</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.442695.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 6073 9704</institution-id><institution>Pharmaceutical Chemistry Department, Faculty of Pharmacy, </institution><institution>Egyptian Russian University, </institution></institution-wrap>Badr City, 11829 Cairo Egypt </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>6</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>6</day><month>8</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>28668</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>4</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par6">In this study, we present an established approach for the UV spectroscopic determination of Hydrochlorothiazide and Triamterene in pharmaceutical mixtures, leveraging the principles of Greenness-by-Design (GbD). By integrating molecular and electronic dynamics simulations, we have developed a greener analytical methodology that significantly reduces time and solvent waste. Our approach focuses on selecting a compromise solvent to minimize peak broadening, thereby enhancing spectral resolution and simplifying the analytical process. This work extends our ongoing efforts to establish the GbD concept in analytical chemistry, building on our previous research to promote sustainable and efficient analytical practices. The developed methods are based on simple mathematical manipulations, including Fourier self-deconvolution, absorption correction, and isoabsorptive point methods, along with ratio spectra approaches such as ratio difference and ratio derivative spectrophotometric methods. The Hydrochlorothiazide and Triamterene were determined with linear ranges of (1&#x02013;18) &#x000b5;g/mL and (1&#x02013;14) &#x000b5;g/mL, respectively. The detection and quantitation limits were in the range of (0.255&#x02013;0.640) &#x000b5;g/mL, and (0.516&#x02013;1.359) &#x000b5;g/mL, which reflects the method&#x02019;s sensitivity. Moreover, a greenness assessment was performed to evaluate the sustainability of the proposed methods, indicating greener outcomes with a considerable reduction of the ecological footprint. This comprehensive approach underscores the potential of GbD in developing efficient, greener analytical methodologies for pharmaceutical analysis.</p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-025-13486-2.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Greenness-by-Design</kwd><kwd>Mathematically manipulated spectral methods</kwd><kwd>Molecular and electronic dynamics simulations</kwd><kwd>Ratio-based UV spectrophotometry</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Sustainability</kwd><kwd>Analytical chemistry</kwd><kwd>Quality control</kwd><kwd>Computational models</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Egyptian Russian University (ERU)</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &#x00026; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB).</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Limited 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par7">The development of green analytical methodologies is an ongoing effort to achieve sustainability in chemistry research. Green analytical techniques are now essential not only for the protection of the environment but also for providing a safe research environment for human personnel<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. The growing development of greenness assessment methods was noticed in the past decade with the reduction of the use of hazardous chemicals being the earliest step in the endeavor to establish green analytical methodologies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Unfortunately, there is a modest effort exerted in developing approaches that merge the greenness concepts within the methodology development process<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>. Several obstacles hinder the integration of green chemistry concepts within analytical methodology development as limited choices and the effectiveness of green chemical reagents and solvents. This major defect can be bypassed by focusing efforts towards renovating methodology development approaches that reduce the overall experimentation required for optimizing the analytical process<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par8">Based on our previous research, the greenness by design (GbD) approach that aims to utilize both in-silico and in-vitro techniques in optimizing an analytical methodology has proven its efficiency in developing green UV spectrophotometric methodologies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. The GbD represents a significant leap towards achieving sustainability in analytical chemistry research. The GbD combines computational simulations with experimental work aiming to reduce the overall ecological footprint of the analytical process. This approach works by simulating the interaction between different solvents and solute molecules (analytes) to uncover the effects of solute-solvent interactions on the spectral interference among various solutes in a mixture. This is accomplished by examining the solute-solvent interactions at both the molecular and electronic levels to calculate several cheminformatics parameters that define how these interactions influence the peak broadening of the solute&#x02019;s UV spectrum. This is achieved through the integration of molecular dynamics simulations (MD) and electronic dynamics (ED) via time-dependent density functional theory (TD-DFT) simulations, which together represent a powerful combination that provides extensive photochemical quantum data regarding the magnitude and nature of the solute-solvent interactions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. By analyzing these data we can compromise the solvent system used in the quantitation process one can choose the solvent with the minimal broadening effect on one or both solutes thus obtaining sharper UV spectral signals and reducing the overall commencing interference between solutes of the same pharmaceutical mixture<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref></sup>. This approach achieves a total reduction in the actual experimental work with reduced analytical effort attaining minimal ecological footprint of the developed methodology.</p><p id="Par9">Thriving the pharmaceutical manufacture process of antihypertensive products is totally based on the development of quantitative analytical methodologies for multicomponent pharmaceutical products<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Hydrochlorothiazide (HCTZ) and Triamterene (TRIM) combination represent an example of a synergistic antihypertensive pharmaceutical mixture through which the patient benefits from the thiazide diuretic (HCTZ) action in lowering his blood pressure and overriding its side effects by another potassium-sparing diuretic (TRIM) which preserves patient&#x02019;s potassium levels avoiding hypokalemia<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>. Reviewing the current literature reveals inadequate analytical techniques for the simultaneous quantitation of that pharmaceutical mixture as spectrophotometric<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup> and chromatographic methods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par10">The reported UV spectrophotometric techniques were established on multivariate regression and wavelet transform which represent lengthy procedures, requiring sophisticated software to manage. Furthermore, the use of lengthy methodologies that require significant time investment may lead to decreased motivation among analysts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. This can result in a suboptimal allocation of cognitive resources and effort, potentially affecting the overall quality of the analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup>. At the same time, the reported chromatographic approaches suffered their inherent elevated organic solvent waste generation limiting their greenness merits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par11">This study builds upon our ongoing research into GbD applications in UV spectroscopy, as outlined in our previous works<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. In this context, we introduce a novel approach that utilizes TD-DFT-generated solute-solvent interaction energies coupled with MD simulations for solvent selection, rather than employing the full package of TD-DFT used in earlier studies to examine gap energies and solvent interactions with both excited and ground states. This streamlined implementation of a computer-aided GbD approach has enabled us to develop greener analytical procedures characterized by low solvent, computational time and energy consumption, thereby contributing to global sustainability goals in pharmaceutical analysis. The proposed methodologies were based on simple mathematically manipulated approaches for the spectral resolution of the investigated pharmaceutical mixture. Moreover, ratio spectra methodologies were also developed as universal UV spectrophotometric approaches to assess the sensitivity and resolution capabilities of the proposed mathematically manipulated methods.</p><p id="Par12">However, it is important to acknowledge some potential limitations of the proposed UV methodologies. These include potential spectral interferences from co-existing substances in complex matrices, relatively lower sensitivity compared to hyphenated techniques (e.g., HPLC-MS), and limited selectivity in multi-component samples without appropriate wavelength selection or derivatization. Furthermore, while UV spectroscopy can effectively distinguish between closely related compounds, challenges may arise in achieving accurate results due to overlapping absorbance spectra. The GbD approach specifically addresses this challenge by optimizing solvent selection to achieve the lowest possible overlap, thereby enhancing the accuracy of the measurements.</p><p id="Par13">Additionally, spectrophotometric methods may face difficulties with turbidity or colored excipients, which can affect absorbance readings. To address these concerns, we have briefly discussed possible strategies to mitigate these limitations, such as applying suitable sample preparation techniques and optimizing analytical parameters to improve reliability and accuracy.</p><p id="Par14">Eventually, multiple greenness assessment protocols were applied to investigate the greenness outcomes of the developed GbD-based methodologies.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Experimental</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Reagents and materials</title><p id="Par15">EPICO, Egypt had generously given free samples of HCTZ and TRIM with proved purity of 99.65 and 98.97%, respectively. Maxzide 25 mg tablets were purchased online from Blink Health online pharmacy, claimed to contain 25 mg of HCTZ and 37.5 mg of TRIM. Ethanol spectroscopic grade was supplied by Honeywell, USA.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Instrument and software</title><p id="Par16">All UV spectrophotometric methodologies were conducted employing Jasco (V-750) UV spectrophotometer assisted by the Spectra Manager software (V.2, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.jascoinc.com/products/spectroscopy/molecular-spectroscopy-software">www.jascoinc.com/products/spectroscopy/molecular-spectroscopy-software</ext-link>). An Elma ultrasonic bath was utilized during the dissolution of standards and the ultrasonic assisted extraction from the investigated dosage form. A Centurion cool centrifuge was also utilized during the sample preparation steps. Molecular dynamic simulations were implemented by Molecular Operating Environment (MOE 2015, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.chemcomp.com/en/index.htm">www.chemcomp.com/en/index.htm</ext-link>) with TD-DFT calculations performed by ORCA (V.4.2.1, orcaforum.kofo.mpg.de/app.php/portal) software utilizing an HP Zbook G3 workstation equipped with an Intel Core i7-6820HQ CPU running at 2.70 GHz<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Procedures</title><sec id="Sec6"><title>Standard stock and sample solutions preparation</title><p id="Par17">Standard stock solutions of both HCTZ and TRIM were prepared by accurately weighing and transferring 10 mg of each drug standard to two separate 100 ml volumetric flask. Seventy milliliters of ethanol were added, and the mixture was shaken for 10 min vigorously and sonicated for another 15 min until complete dissolution was achieved attaining a homogenous clear solution. Finally, the volumes were adjusted using ethanol to obtain a standard solution of 100 &#x000b5;g/mL of each drug.</p><p id="Par18">For sample preparation, ten tablets of Maxzide were finely ground, and an equivalent weight of one tablet was accurately measured and transferred to a 100 mL volumetric flask containing 70 mL of ethanol. The flask was sealed and shaken vigorously for 5 min, then subjected to ultrasonic dissolution for 20 min. After reaching room temperature, the volume was adjusted to the mark with ethanol.</p><p id="Par19">A suitable aliquot was then transferred to a 50 mL Falcon tube for centrifugation at 10,000 rpm for 5 min. From the clear supernatant, 1 mL was withdrawn and quantitatively transferred into a 10 mL volumetric flask, where the volume was completed. Finally, an appropriate aliquot was taken from this flask and transferred to another 10 mL volumetric flask, with the volume completed using ethanol to achieve concentrations of 4 &#x000b5;g/mL for HCTZ and 6 &#x000b5;g/mL for TRIM. A suitable volume from this final solution was then transferred to a quartz cuvette for UV spectrophotometric scanning, using ethanol as the blank. Finally, the content of the tablet dosage form was assessed using the appropriate regression equation from each developed methodology.</p></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Calibration curves construction</title><p id="Par20">Calibration of the investigated drugs was achieved utilizing Jasco double beam spectrophotometer and all measurements were performed against ethanol as a blank.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Absorption correction method (ACM)</title><p id="Par21">HCTZ and TRIM aliquots were properly obtained from their corresponding standard solutions, transferred into two sets of 10 mL volumetric flasks, and the remainder of the volume was adjusted with ethanol to generate concentration ranges of (4&#x02013;18 &#x000b5;g/mL) and (2&#x02013;14 &#x000b5;g/mL) for HCTZ and TRIM, respectively.</p><p id="Par22">Each absorption spectrum was recorded versus ethanol as a baseline. The absorbance values of HCTZ at 271 nm (&#x003bb; <sub>max</sub>) and TRIM at 271 and 361 nm were then plotted versus each relevant concentration in (&#x000b5;g/mL) for each component, and a correction factor (F<sub>ac</sub>) for TRIM at the corresponding wavelengths was derived to eliminate its interfering action with HCTZ at 271 nm.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Fourier self-deconvolution (FSD)</title><p id="Par23">To prepare HCTZ and TRIM serial dilutions, the same technique outlined in standard stock solutions preparation was used. The zero-order absorption spectra of each component concentration vs. ethanol were recorded. Each recorded spectrum was deconvoluted using the FSD algorithm included in the spectra manager operating software with the Full width at half maximum (FWHM&#x02009;=&#x02009;90). The amplitudes of HCTZ at 299 nm and TRIM at 366 nm were then plotted vs. each component&#x02019;s concentration in (&#x000b5;g/mL).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Isoabsorptive point method (ISM)</title><p id="Par24">Several aliquots of HCTZ and TRIM were accurately extracted from individual stock solutions and placed into a sequence of 10 mL volumetric flasks to produce different dilutions within the ranges of 1&#x02013;18 &#x000b5;g/mL and 1&#x02013;14 &#x000b5;g/mL, respectively. Each standard solution was analyzed separately with ethanol as a diluent, following which the absorbance levels for HCTZ and TRIM were recorded at 266.8 nm. A calibration was plotted for the concentration of HCTZ versus its corresponding absorbance at 266.8 nm then a regression equation was set up to predict the total concentration of both HCTZ and TRIM at the isoabsorptive point 266.8 nm in their prepared laboratory mixtures and pharmaceutical dosage forms. Finally, the pure concentration of TRIM was determined at the zero order spectrum at the no contribution point 361 nm.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Ratio spectra spectrophotometric methods</title><sec id="Sec12"><title>Ratio difference spectrophotometric method (RDF)</title><p id="Par25">Standard solutions of HCTZ and TRIM with concentrations (1&#x02013;18 &#x000b5;g/mL) and (1&#x02013;14 &#x000b5;g/mL), respectively, were prepared following the procedure outlined under stock solution preparation. The absorption spectrum for each drug solution was recorded against ethanol as a blank. Subsequently, the spectrum of HCTZ was divided by the spectrum of TRIM (10 &#x000b5;g/mL) as the divisor, while the spectrum of TRIM was divided by the spectrum of HCTZ (4 &#x000b5;g/mL) as the divisor. The differences in amplitudes of the resulting ratio spectra were calculated at &#x00394;P (273&#x02013;293 nm) for HCTZ and &#x00394;P (244&#x02013;274 nm) for TRIM. These differences were then plotted against the corresponding concentrations (&#x000b5;g/mL) for each component.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Ratio derivative spectrophotometric method (RDM)</title><p id="Par26">The procedure described in standard stock solutions preparation was utilized to prepare serial dilutions of HCTZ and TRIM across a concentration range of (1&#x02013;18 &#x000b5;g/mL) and (1&#x02013;14 &#x000b5;g/mL) for both compounds. Subsequently, the zero-order absorption spectra for HCTZ and TRIM were obtained. These spectra were then divided by the spectra of TRIM and HCTZ by their respective concentrations of 4 &#x00026; 10 &#x000b5;g/mL, respectively, thus serving as the divisors. The resulting ratio spectra were analyzed to compute the first derivative, and the corresponding amplitudes at 283 nm and 251 nm were recorded for the quantification of HCTZ and TRIM, respectively.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec100"><title>Molecular and electronic dynamics &#x00026; photochemical quantum investigations</title><p id="Par27">MD simulations were performed utilizing molecular operating environment 2015 (MOE) based on the Amber: EHT10 force-field<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref></sup> to investigate the behavior of both HCTZ and TRIM in different solvent environment (water, methanol, acetonitrile and ethanol). Various descriptors as solvation energy, hydrogen bonding and non-bonding interaction energies were calculated for both molecules in each solvated environment. The TD-DFT calculations were implemented based on the orca software utilizing the B3LYP hybrid functional assisted by the RIJCOSX functional<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup> and the polarized triple-zeta basis set (def2-TZVP). The conductor-like polarizable continuum model (CPCM) solvation model was utilized to simulate the effect of different investigated solvents. After normal convergence of the preceded calculations, the solute-solvent interaction energies were calculated.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Results and discussion</title><p id="Par28">The application of Green by Design (GbD) in UV spectroscopy has proven effective in developing environmentally friendly spectrophotometric methods<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. In this study, we conducted extensive molecular mechanical, photochemical quantum and electronic dynamics investigations on a binary mixture of HCTZ and TRIM to explore how different solvents affect the interference between the UV spectral signals of these drug molecules.</p><p id="Par29">Using MD simulations, we calculated several cheminformatic descriptors, including hydrogen bonding capacity, solvation energy, and non-bonded interactions within each solvent environment. Additionally, TD-DFT calculations were performed to examine solute-solvent interactions and the corresponding dipole moments for each drug molecule in various solvents. The data obtained from both MD and TD-DFT simulations were helpful in optimizing the solvent system for developing UV spectroscopic methodologies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. Our goal was to minimize spectral interference between the two drugs and reduce the analytical effort required to differentiate their signals in combined dosage forms.</p><p id="Par30">Building on this foundation, our current work implements the GbD approach to identify a suitable solvent that achieves optimal spectral resolution for the pharmaceutical mixture under study (Figure<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>). Traditional laboratory testing of various solvents often results in significant waste; however, the in-vitro GbD approach minimizes waste by confining it to the application stage. Furthermore, this method reduces analysis time and effort by enhancing spectral resolution, thereby decreasing the analytical workload compared to conventional UV spectroscopic methods.</p><p id="Par31">When compared to other analytical approaches<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup> such as classical solvent screening and trial-and-error methods, the GbD approach not only streamlines the process but also enhances efficiency and sustainability in green analytical chemistry. This comparative advantage highlights the potential of GbD as a more effective alternative for solvent selection in spectroscopic applications.</p><sec id="Sec16"><title>Molecular dynamics simulation</title><p id="Par32">After the 760 Ps simulation, the trajectory files for each drug in each solvated environment was analyzed regarding solvation, interaction energy, and hydrogen bonding capacity. The analysis of solvation energies revealed an endothermic behavior of both HCTZ and TRIM in methanol, ethanol and acetonitrile, while showing an exothermic dissolution pattern in water as in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. The hydrogen bonding (HB) capacities of HCTZ and TRIM in the investigated solvents were found to correlate with their respective solvation profiles. Both molecules exhibited higher HB capacities in methanol and ethanol, while showing significantly lower capacities in acetonitrile, with the lowest observed in a water environment, as illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>.</p><p id="Par33">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Solvation energy profile for both HCTZ and TRIM in water, ethanol, methanol and acetonitrile.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_13486_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par34">
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Hydrogen bonding capacity for both HCTZ and TRIM in water, ethanol, methanol and acetonitrile.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_13486_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par35">Methanol and ethanol effectively interacted with both HCTZ and TRIM, facilitating the establishment of hydrogen bonds. In contrast, acetonitrile, being an aprotic solvent, demonstrated lower HB capacities for both molecules compared to methanol and ethanol.</p><p id="Par36">In the case of water, we propose that the observed lowest HB capacities can be attributed to the unique characteristics of water as a solvent. Water possesses a robust intramolecular hydrogen bonding network that extensively solvates solute molecules. This extensive solvation can inhibit effective solute-solvent hydrogen bond formation due to steric hindrance and competition from surrounding solvent molecules. Thus, the strong hydrogen bonding interactions within the water network may limit the availability of hydrogen bond sites for solute interactions, further explaining the reduced HB capacities observed in this solvent<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par37">The analysis of the interaction energies profile for the two molecules in the four solvents was very complex due to interfering interaction profiles for both drugs in the investigated solvents as in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>.</p><p id="Par38">
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Interaction energy plot for both HCTZ and TRIM in water, ethanol, methanol and acetonitrile.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_13486_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par39">The initial analysis of the data obtained from MD simulations provided compelling evidence of significant interactions between the water solvent and both HCTZ and TRIM. These findings prompted us to initially exclude water from further consideration, given the exothermic dissolution behavior of both compounds in aqueous environments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref></sup>. The interactions between solute and solvent are critical factors influencing the resolution of UV spectra in their pharmaceutical mixtures. Understanding the nature and magnitude of these interactions necessitates further investigation at the sub-molecular level to elucidate their extent and implications for the analytical efforts required to resolve the investigated mixture.</p></sec><sec id="Sec17"><title>Electronic dynamics and photochemical quantum investigations</title><p id="Par40">In this study, we utilized the B3LYP hybrid functional, supported by the RIJCOSX functional and the def2-TZVP basis set, to investigate solute-solvent interaction energies critical to our GbD methodology in UV spectroscopy. The B3LYP functional is recognized for its balance of computational efficiency and accuracy in predicting electronic properties, effectively capturing the physics of excited states. The RIJCOSX functional enhances computational efficiency by reducing the scaling of calculations, allowing for faster evaluations of electron repulsion integrals, particularly beneficial for larger systems with multiple solvent interactions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref></sup>. The def2-TZVP basis set provides an optimal balance between computational demand and detail, enabling accurate electronic structure calculations and improved representation of electron distribution in excited states. Together, these parameters create a robust framework for our analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par41">The TD-DFT calculations yielded comprehensive data regarding the electronic configurations and excited states of the investigated compounds. Furthermore, these calculations provided valuable insights into the energy characteristics of the solvated systems and variations in dipole moments of each compound within different solvent environments. These parameters were crucial for establishing a relationship between the solvent systems employed and their effects on the spectral broadening of the investigated compounds.</p><p id="Par42">The observed consistency between the calculated molecular dipole moments and the polarity of the solvents, as indicated by the dielectric constant (&#x0025b;), demonstrated the influence of solvent-induced polarization on the solute<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup>. This alignment further validates the accuracy of the DFT calculations, as illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a.</p><p id="Par43">
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p><bold>(a)</bold> Molecular dipole moment for both HCTZ and TRIM in different solvents versus solvent dielectric constant. <bold>(b)</bold> Hydrophobic mapping for both HCTZ and TRIM showing lipophilic/hydrophilic molecular surface area. This figure was created by the authors using the Molecular Operating Environment (MOE 2015) and its molecular surface lipophilicity mapping tool. For more information, please visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.chemcomp.com">https://www.chemcomp.com</ext-link>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_13486_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par44">Additionally, the investigation of the molecular dipole moment provided valuable insights into the molecular polarity and the influence of various solvents on the investigated compounds. TRIM was found to be less polar than HCTZ, with dipole moment values ranging from 4.313 to 4.388 Debye. In contrast, HCTZ exhibited dipole moment values ranging from 13.520 to 13.687 Debye, indicating a significantly higher polarity. Moreover, the hydrophobicity mapping of both molecules revealed a larger hydrophobic center on TRIM in comparison with HCTZ as shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b<bold>.</bold> These observations suggest that different solute-solvent interaction behaviors are expected within the solvated molecular systems of both compounds.</p><p id="Par45">Given that HCTZ is the more polar compound, it is anticipated to be particularly sensitive to solvent interactions, especially with highly polar solvents such as water. These interactions may result in notable changes in its UV spectrum, manifesting as shifts in peak position and broadening of absorption peaks.</p><p id="Par46">The interaction energies between the outermost valence shell electrons of TRIM and HCTZ with their surrounding solvent molecules were also investigated and are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>. HCTZ exhibited the highest interaction energies with water, consistent with its exothermic behavior in an aqueous environment as observed from MD simulations. This finding led to the exclusion of water as a potential solvent for UV spectroscopic analysis, as the higher solvent interactions with the molecule, the greater broadening of its spectral peaks was observed, increasing the chance of interference with other molecular signals in a pharmaceutical mixture. Conversely, HCTZ showed the lowest interactions with ethanol making it a potential candidate for UV spectral measurements.</p><p id="Par47">
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Solute-solvent interaction energies for HCTZ and TRIM in different solvents calculated by TD-DFT simulation.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_13486_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par48">For TRIM, water was the least interactive solvent, followed by methanol, acetonitrile, and finally ethanol, as shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>. Although water showed the least interaction energy with TRIM it showed an exothermic pattern of dissolution in reverse to expectations as seen in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. This anomaly can be illustrated by revising the structural properties of TRIM, due to its elevated hydrophobicity it causes disruption of the hydrogen bond network between water molecules forcing them to reorganize in more stable molecular arrangement around the hydrophobic regions of the solute<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup> which eventually result in energy release to the system so that the dissolution profile seems to be exothermic despite the lower solute-solvent interactions.</p><p id="Par49">The rationale behind solvent selection is well supported by both MD and TD-DFT data. While our findings indicate that ethanol minimally interacts with HCTZ and significantly interacts with TRIM, it is important to note that the mixture of HCTZ and TRIM exhibits a one-way interaction. Specifically, the main peak of TRIM, when measured in ethanol, aligns at 361 nm, which coincides with a region of minimal contribution from HCTZ due to the solvent&#x02019;s narrowing effect on HCTZ&#x02019;s peaks at 271 nm and 221 nm.</p><p id="Par50">As illustrated in Figure <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2a</xref>, the comparison of interaction energies reveals a significantly stronger interaction between ethanol and TRIM compared to HCTZ, supporting the notion of ethanol&#x02019;s selective solvation properties. This enhanced interaction with TRIM is crucial for its solubility and stability in solution. Furthermore, Figure <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2b</xref> shows the full range overlay spectra of both HCTZ and TRIM in ethanol, highlighting how ethanol broadens the TRIM peaks, particularly its n-&#x003c0;* transition at 361 nm, while exerting a less significant broadening effect on the HCTZ peaks. This characteristic simplifies the analytical task of resolving the two compounds, especially when employing simple straightforward methodologies such as the ACM, FSD and ISM methods.</p><p id="Par51">Thus, despite the differing interaction strengths, the solvent ethanol facilitates effective separation and analysis of HCTZ and TRIM, reinforcing its selection as the optimal solvent for our study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Spectrophotometric approaches</title><sec id="Sec19"><title>Absorption correction method (ACM)</title><p id="Par52">In ACM, a simple mathematical technique was utilized to analyze the binary mixture of HCTZ and TRIM by focusing on the extended regions of their overlapping spectra<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. The concentration of TRIM was effectively determined using its zero-contributing segment at 361 nm within the overlapping spectra. To mitigate interference at the &#x003bb; <sub>max</sub> of HCTZ, an interference-correcting factor (F<sub>ac</sub>) was established for TRIM. This factor was derived by dividing the absorbance of TRIM at 271 nm by its absorbance at 361 nm.</p><p id="Par53">A calibration curve for TRIM was created at 361 nm across a concentration range of 2&#x02013;14 &#x000b5;g/mL (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>), and the associated regression equation, detailed in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, was used to ascertain its concentration in both laboratory-prepared mixtures (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) and pharmaceutical samples (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Importantly, the absorbance measured at 271 nm, which aligns with the &#x003bb; <sub>max</sub> of HCTZ, does not provide an accurate representation of pure HCTZ concentration due to ongoing interference from TRIM at this wavelength (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).</p><p id="Par54">
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Zero-order UV overlain spectra of both HCTZ and TRIM, each at a concentration of 10 &#x000b5;g/mL, illustrating the determination of both drugs at 271 and 361 nm, respectively by the absorption correction method.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_13486_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par55">
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Regression and validation data for the determination of HCTZ and TRIM by the proposed spectrophotometric methods.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Parameters</th><th align="left" colspan="5">HCTZ</th><th align="left" colspan="5">TRIM</th></tr><tr><th align="left">FSD</th><th align="left">ISM</th><th align="left">ACM</th><th align="left">RDF</th><th align="left">RDM</th><th align="left">FSD</th><th align="left">ISM</th><th align="left">ACM</th><th align="left">RDF</th><th align="left">RDM</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Wavelength (nm)<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">299</td><td align="left">266.8</td><td align="left">271</td><td align="left">&#x00394; 273&#x02013;293</td><td align="left">283</td><td align="left">366</td><td align="left">361</td><td align="left">361</td><td align="left">&#x00394; 244&#x02013;274</td><td align="left">251</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Calibration range (&#x000b5;g/ml)</td><td align="left">1&#x02013;18</td><td align="left">2&#x02013;16</td><td align="left">4&#x02013;18</td><td align="left">1&#x02013;18</td><td align="left">1&#x02013;18</td><td align="left">2&#x02013;12</td><td align="left">2&#x02013;14</td><td align="left">2&#x02013;14</td><td align="left">1&#x02013;14</td><td align="left">1&#x02013;14</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Slope</td><td align="left">0.0879</td><td align="left">0.0569</td><td align="left">0.0690</td><td align="left">0.0860</td><td align="left">0.0062</td><td align="left">0.1768</td><td align="left">0.0803</td><td align="left">0.0803</td><td align="left">1.007</td><td align="left">0.065395</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Intercept</td><td align="left">0.0184</td><td align="left">0.0031</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.0517</td><td align="left">0.0083</td><td align="left">0.0010</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.0573</td><td align="left">0.0049</td><td align="left">0.0051</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.0550</td><td align="left">&#x02212;0.02194</td></tr><tr><td align="left">r</td><td align="left">0.9998</td><td align="left">0.9995</td><td align="left">0.9992</td><td align="left">0.9999</td><td align="left">0.9997</td><td align="left">0.9996</td><td align="left">0.9993</td><td align="left">0.9995</td><td align="left">0.9997</td><td align="left">0.9996</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><p>LOD</p><p>(&#x000b5;g/mL)</p></td><td align="left">0.255</td><td align="left">0.378</td><td align="left">0.640</td><td align="left">0.170</td><td align="left">0.319</td><td align="left">0.449</td><td align="left">0.352</td><td align="left">0.352</td><td align="left">0.283</td><td align="left">0.318</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><p>LOQ</p><p>(&#x000b5;g/mL)</p></td><td align="left">0.774</td><td align="left">1.147</td><td align="left">1.939</td><td align="left">0.516</td><td align="left">0.964</td><td align="left">1.359</td><td align="left">1.068</td><td align="left">1.068</td><td align="left">0.857</td><td align="left">0.962</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2"><p>Accuracy <sup>b</sup></p><p>(% RSD)</p></td><td align="left">99.12</td><td align="left">99.58</td><td align="left">100.11</td><td align="left">99.97</td><td align="left">99.96</td><td align="left">100.41</td><td align="left">99.01</td><td align="left">99.85</td><td align="left">100.73</td><td align="left">100.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left">0.521</td><td align="left">0.556</td><td align="left">0.782</td><td align="left">0.144</td><td align="left">0.544</td><td align="left">0.631</td><td align="left">0.801</td><td align="left">0.675</td><td align="left">0.685</td><td align="left">1.72</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><p>Precision</p><p>(% RSD) <sup>c</sup></p><p>- Repeatability</p><p>- Intermediate precision</p></td><td align="left"><p>0.452</p><p>0.852</p></td><td align="left"><p>0.585</p><p>0.732</p></td><td align="left"><p>0.771</p><p>1.011</p></td><td align="left"><p>0.189</p><p>0.326</p></td><td align="left"><p>1.67</p><p>1.86</p></td><td align="left"><p>0.784</p><p>0.986</p></td><td align="left"><p>0.544</p><p>1.241</p></td><td align="left"><p>0.673</p><p>1.854</p></td><td align="left"><p>0.659</p><p>0.731</p></td><td align="left"><p>2.434</p><p>2.479</p></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup> The peak amplitude of measurement of each proposed method.</p><p><sup>b</sup> Average of nine determinations (three concentrations repeated three times).</p><p><sup>c</sup> % RSD of nine determinations (three concentrations repeated three times).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par56">
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Determination of HCTZ and TRIM in their laboratory prepared mixtures by the proposed UV spectrophotometric methods.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">HCTZ</th><th align="left">TRIM</th><th align="left" colspan="10">% Recovery <sup>a</sup></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="2">conc. (&#x000b5;g/ml)</th><th align="left" colspan="6">HCTZ</th><th align="left" colspan="4">TRIM</th></tr><tr><th align="left">FSD</th><th align="left">ISM</th><th align="left">ACM</th><th align="left">RDF</th><th align="left">RDM</th><th align="left">FSD</th><th align="left">ISM</th><th align="left">ACM</th><th align="left">RDF</th><th align="left">RDM</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">99.96</td><td align="left">98.05</td><td align="left">99.19</td><td align="left">99.69</td><td align="left">100.56</td><td align="left">100.75</td><td align="left">99.66</td><td align="left">99.66</td><td align="left">99.88</td><td align="left">98.62</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">99.97</td><td align="left">99.43</td><td align="left">99.24</td><td align="left">100.78</td><td align="left">99.65</td><td align="left">100.18</td><td align="left">98.39</td><td align="left">98.39</td><td align="left">98.01</td><td align="left">98.87</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">99.58</td><td align="left">99.08</td><td align="left">100.62</td><td align="left">98.52</td><td align="left">100.97</td><td align="left">101.85</td><td align="left">100.47</td><td align="left">100.47</td><td align="left">100.74</td><td align="left">100.41</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">99.47</td><td align="left">100.29</td><td align="left">99.60</td><td align="left">101.72</td><td align="left">98.14</td><td align="left">100.90</td><td align="left">100.05</td><td align="left">100.05</td><td align="left">98.71</td><td align="left">99.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">98.69</td><td align="left">98.06</td><td align="left">99.15</td><td align="left">100.16</td><td align="left">101.02</td><td align="left">99.86</td><td align="left">99.52</td><td align="left">99.52</td><td align="left">99.43</td><td align="left">99.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2"><p>Mean &#x000b1;</p><p>SD</p></td><td align="left">99.53&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.522</td><td align="left">98.98&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.951</td><td align="left">99.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.618</td><td align="left">100.17&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.19</td><td align="left">100.07&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.21</td><td align="left"><p>100.71</p><p>&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.767</p></td><td align="left">99.62&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.778</td><td align="left">99.62&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.778</td><td align="left">99.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.05</td><td align="left"><p>99.26&#x000b1;</p><p>0.627</p></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup> average of three determinations.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par57">
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Determination of HCTZ and TRIM in the prepared dosage form by the proposed spectrophotometric and reported methods.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3">Parameters</th><th align="left" colspan="12">Proposed methods</th></tr><tr><th align="left" colspan="5">HCTZ</th><th align="left" colspan="5">TRIM</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Reported methods</th></tr><tr><th align="left">FSD</th><th align="left">ISM</th><th align="left">ACM</th><th align="left">RDF</th><th align="left">RDM</th><th align="left">FSD</th><th align="left">ISM</th><th align="left">ACM</th><th align="left">RDF</th><th align="left">RDM</th><th align="left">HCTZ</th><th align="left">TRIM</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Number of measurements</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean % recovery <sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">99.57</td><td align="left">99.46</td><td align="left">99.86</td><td align="left">100.23</td><td align="left">100.89</td><td align="left">100.59</td><td align="left">99.64</td><td align="left">99.64</td><td align="left">100.09</td><td align="left">100.87</td><td align="left">101.22</td><td align="left">101.65</td></tr><tr><td align="left">% RSD</td><td align="left">1.138</td><td align="left">1.629</td><td align="left">1.600</td><td align="left">1.54</td><td align="left">1.24</td><td align="left">0.339</td><td align="left">1.317</td><td align="left">1.317</td><td align="left">0.78</td><td align="left">0.87</td><td align="left">0.634</td><td align="left">1.044</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Variance</td><td align="left">1.295</td><td align="left">2.655</td><td align="left">2.560</td><td align="left">2.372</td><td align="left">1.54</td><td align="left">0.038</td><td align="left">1.755</td><td align="left">1.755</td><td align="left">0.608</td><td align="left">0.757</td><td align="left">0.402</td><td align="left">1.090</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><p>Student&#x02019;s</p><p>t-test <sup>b</sup></p></td><td align="left">2.20</td><td align="left">1.75</td><td align="left">1.37</td><td align="left">0.830</td><td align="left">0.308</td><td align="left">1.68</td><td align="left">2.08</td><td align="left">2.08</td><td align="left">2. 07</td><td align="left">0.994</td><td align="left"><p>-</p><p>(2.78)</p></td><td align="left"><p>-</p><p>(2.78)</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left">F-value <sup>b</sup></td><td align="left">0.31</td><td align="left">0.15</td><td align="left">0.16</td><td align="left">1.245</td><td align="left">1.24</td><td align="left">0.11</td><td align="left">0.63</td><td align="left">0.63</td><td align="left">1.79</td><td align="left">1.44</td><td align="left"><p>-</p><p>(19)</p></td><td align="left"><p>-</p><p>(19)</p></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup> average of three determinations.</p><p><sup>b</sup> The values in parenthesis are tabulated values of &#x0201c;t&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;F&#x0201d; at confidence interval 95% (<italic>P</italic>&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.05).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par58">To determine the concentration of HCTZ, the absorbance of TRIM at 361 nm, adjusted by the F<sub>ac</sub>, must be subtracted from the absorbance of HCTZ at 271 nm across a concentration range of 4&#x02013;18 &#x000b5;g/mL. This relationship can be expressed as &#x00394;P (271 nm <sub>HCTZ</sub> &#x02013; (361 nm <sub>TRIM</sub> &#x000d7; F<sub>ac</sub>)).</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Fourier self-deconvolution (FSD)</title><p id="Par59">FSD is a computational technique utilized to resolve overlapping spectral peaks by effectively narrowing their bandwidths, thereby facilitating the differentiation of individual peaks. As proposed by Kauppinen<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>FSD addresses the instrumental distortions inherent in spectrophotometric measurements, defined as physical convolution, where the measured spectrum M(v) can be expressed as:<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1379">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$M{\text{ }}\left( v \right){\text{ }} = {\text{ }}E{\text{ }}\left( v \right){\text{ }}*{\text{ }}G{\text{ }}\left( v \right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_13486_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par60">Here, G (v) represents the instrumental distortion function, and * denotes the convolution integral. FSD reverses this convolution process, allowing for the extraction of the original spectrum E (v) through the inverse Fourier transformation:<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1387">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$IE(x) = \frac{1}{{{F^{ - 1}}\;(G\;(v))}}IM(x)$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_13486_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par61">The final form of E (v) can be derived as:</p><p id="Par62">
<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="d33e1397">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$E (v) =\:\:F\left\{\frac{D\:(L,\:x)}{\text{exp}\left\{\pi\:\sigma\:\left|x\right|\right\}}\right\}*M\:\left(v\right)$$\end{document}</tex-math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_13486_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>
</p><p id="Par63">In this context, an apodization function D (L, x) is employed to mitigate the effects of noise, which can significantly impact spectral clarity. The trade-off between resolution and signal intensity is quantitatively assessed through the signal-to-noise ratio (SNR). FSD is used in UV spectroscopy to enhance spectral resolution by making overlapping peaks more distinguishable along the wavelength (X) axis. This technique works by mathematically reducing peak broadening, which helps reveal individual components in complex spectra. However, this improvement in resolution can come at the cost of intensity (Y-axis) information, as FSD may amplify noise especially in low-signal regions.</p><p id="Par64">While this doesn&#x02019;t always lead to a higher SNR in the conventional sense, it often improves the apparent SNR by making the peaks easier to differentiate. As a result, FSD enables more accurate identification and semi-quantitative analysis of overlapping signals when applied carefully<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par65">In our study, we leveraged the GbD approach to simultaneously determine both HCTZ and TRIM in their binary mixture. A significant limitation of FSD is its inability to distinguish between components in a binary mixture due to extensive overlap in their spectral signals. However, in our specific mixture, TRIM was prominently situated in the zero-contribution zone of the overlapped spectra, facilitating its resolution from HCTZ. Conversely, resolving HCTZ from TRIM posed a challenge due to considerable overlap around the &#x003bb; <sub>max</sub> of HCTZ. The GbD approach was influential in this context, allowing us to select an appropriate solvent that minimizes spectral interference and maintains narrow spectral bandwidths for both compounds. This reduction in overlap significantly aided FSD in the simultaneous resolution of both compounds in their binary pharmaceutical mixture<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par66">By applying the FSD method, we successfully resolved both HCTZ and TRIM. The zero-order spectra of HCTZ and TRIM were recorded and subsequently deconvoluted as outlined previously. A calibration curve was then constructed by plotting the amplitudes of the deconvoluted spectra of HCTZ and TRIM at 299 nm and 366 nm, respectively, against their corresponding concentrations (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a&#x00026;b). Each regression equation was utilized to determine the concentrations of HCTZ and TRIM in both laboratory-prepared mixtures (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>) and formulated dosage forms (Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>).</p><p id="Par67">
<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p><bold>(a)</bold> Deconvoluted overlain UV spectra of both HCTZ and TRIM for the determination of HCTZ at 299 nm by Fourier self-deconvolution method. <bold>(b)</bold> Deconvoluted overlain UV spectra of both HCTZ and TRIM for the determination of TRIM at 366 nm by Fourier self-deconvolution method.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_13486_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Isoabsorptive point method (ISM)</title><p id="Par68">The ISM is a straightforward mathematical approach used to resolve spectral interference in a binary mixture, particularly when one component can be determined at its &#x003bb; <sub>max</sub> with zero contribution from the second component<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. This method relies on the isoabsorptive point, where both components contribute equally to the overall absorbance. In our study, HCTZ and TRIM exhibited an isoabsorptive point at 266.8 nm (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). A calibration curve for HCTZ was established over the concentration range of 1&#x02013;18 &#x000b5;g/mL, and the resulting regression equation was employed to determine the total concentrations of both TRIM and HCTZ in pharmaceutical dosage forms and laboratory-prepared mixtures.</p><p id="Par69">
<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>UV overlain spectra of HCTZ and TRIM (12 &#x000b5;g/mL) with their synthetic mixture (6 &#x000b5;g/mL of each) showing their isoabsorptive point at 266.8 nm.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_13486_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par70">TRIM was easily quantified at 361 nm without interference from HCTZ. Consequently, the pure concentration of HCTZ in the dosage form was calculated by subtracting the concentration of TRIM from the total concentration determined at 266.8 nm. ISM is highly selective when one component can be measured at its &#x003bb; <sub>max</sub> with no contribution from the other component (HCTZ). This makes it ideal for scenarios where such conditions are met. The method is sensitive within the defined concentration range (2&#x02013;16 &#x000b5;g/mL for HCTZ and 2&#x02013;14 &#x000b5;g/mL for TRIM), allowing for precise quantification. ISM typically requires fewer manipulations, contributing to a more environmentally friendly analytical process.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Ratio difference spectrophotometric method (RDF)</title><p id="Par71">Achieving successful spectrophotometric analyses necessitates careful selection of divisor concentrations and appropriate wavelength pairs<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. A range of concentrations for each divisor was assessed to determine the most effective parameters. For quantifying HCTZ, TRIM at 10 &#x000b5;g/mL was employed as a divisor to minimize interference, while HCTZ at 4 &#x000b5;g/mL was chosen as the divisor for TRIM. This selection was based on criteria such as repeatability, signal-to-noise ratio, recovery percentage, and the linearity of the resulting ratio spectra observed during preliminary trials.</p><p id="Par72">It is essential that the selected wavelength pairs exhibit clear peak amplitudes in their ratio spectra. Satisfactory linearity was confirmed at each wavelength independently. Several wavelength pairs were tested for their quantification effectiveness, with (&#x00394;P273&#x02013;293 nm) and (&#x00394;P244&#x02013;274 nm) identified as the most suitable for determining HCTZ (Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>a) and TRIM (Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>b), respectively. The absolute amplitude differences at these wavelength pairs were found to be directly proportional to the concentrations of the analytes studied (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p><p id="Par73">
<fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><p><bold>(a)</bold> Ratio spectrum of HCTZ using 10 &#x000b5;g/mL TRIM as a devisor showing difference points at 273 and 293 nm for the determination of HCTZ by the ratio difference spectrophotometric method. (<bold>b)</bold> Ratio spectrum of TRIM using 4 &#x000b5;g/mL HCTZ as a devisor showing difference points at 244 and 274 nm for the determination of TRIM by the ratio difference spectrophotometric method. <bold>(c)</bold> First derivative of the ratio spectrum of HCTZ using 10 &#x000b5;g/mL TRIM as a devisor for the determination of HCTZ at 283 nm by the ratio derivative spectrophotometric method. (d<bold>)</bold> First derivative of the ratio spectrum of TRIM using 4 &#x000b5;g/mL HCTZ as a devisor for the determination of TRIM at 251 nm by the ratio derivative spectrophotometric method.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_13486_Fig9_HTML" id="MO9"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par74">Ratio spectra based methodologies can achieve selectivity by carefully choosing divisor concentrations and wavelength pairs that minimize interference. The sensitivity of RDF is contingent upon the choice of divisor concentrations and the clarity of the ratio spectra. Optimal conditions were identified during preliminary trials, ensuring reliable measurements. As ratio spectra based methodologies require several preliminary trials to optimize its selectivity and sensitivity it can be considered relatively green in comparison to more straightforward methods as FSD or ISM.</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Ratio derivative spectrophotometric method (RDM)</title><p id="Par75">Several parameters were optimized, including the divisor concentration, selection of the measurement wavelength (&#x003bb;), and linearity of the resulting ratio spectra. Based on these criteria, the optimal divisors identified were TRIM at 10 &#x000b5;g/mL for the determination of HCTZ (Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>c) and HCTZ at 4 &#x000b5;g/mL for the quantification of TRIM (Fig. <xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>d). The obtained ratio spectra were subsequently analyzed to compute the first derivative of the ratio spectra. Calibration curves were generated by plotting the amplitudes at 283 nm for HCTZ and at 251 nm for TRIM against their respective concentrations, with the regression data presented in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec101"><title>Greenness assessment of the GbD based approaches</title><p id="Par76">The assessment of greenness in analytical methodologies has traditionally relied on various metrics that evaluate the development stages of these methods according to a predetermined scoring system. A persistent challenge has been the integration of greenness within the earliest stages of method development to ensure a reduced ecological footprint. Fortunately, the GbD approach addresses this challenge by employing a combined in-silico and in-vitro investigation strategy, optimizing method parameters to achieve desired analytical goals with minimal ecological impact.</p><p id="Par77">The incorporation of the GbD approach in UV spectroscopic methodologies necessitated the examination of various solvent systems and their effects on the spectral bandwidths of pharmaceutical compounds in mixtures. This was accomplished through computer-based simulations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup> including dynamic simulations and photochemical quantum approaches. These in-silico techniques allowed us to explore the relationship between solvent systems and solute molecules, enhancing our understanding of photochemical quantum phenomena, particularly the extent of peak broadening in their spectra due to solute-solvent interactions. This strategy facilitated the development of analytical methodologies that reduced analytical effort while minimizing time, energy, and chemical waste<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par78">To evaluate the greenness of the GbD-based methodologies, we applied two assessment protocols, including the AGREE (Analytical Greenness metric) and the Green Analytical Procedure Index (GAPI). The AGREE approach is a contemporary metric developed to quantitatively evaluate the environmental sustainability of analytical procedures. It is founded on the twelve principles of Green Analytical Chemistry (GAC)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref></sup> with each principle assessed individually and scored from 0 (non-green) to 1 (fully green). These principles account for factors such as solvent and reagent safety, energy use, waste production, sample throughput, and overall method efficiency<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par79">To calculate the AGREE score, normalized values are assigned to each of the twelve principles based on method-specific data. These are then averaged to produce a final score between 0 and 1, reflecting the overall greenness of the method. This score is visually communicated through a circular pictogram divided into 12 colored sections green for strong compliance, yellow for moderate, and red for weak with the numerical score placed at the center. This format enables a clear, at-a-glance understanding of both the strengths and limitations of a given method from a sustainability perspective.</p><p id="Par80">In our current work, the AGREE evaluation was performed using the official AGREE software. The developed method achieved a high score of 0.81 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref><bold>(a)</bold>), confirming its strong alignment with green chemistry principles. By comparison, the previously reported method yielded a lower AGREE score of 0.69 (Fig. <xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref><bold>(b)</bold>), indicating higher environmental burden<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. This clearly demonstrates that the proposed method is not only analytically effective but also significantly greener and more eco-friendly than the existing approach<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par81">
<fig id="Fig10"><label>Fig. 10</label><caption><p><bold>(a)</bold> Application of AGREE metric to assess the greenness of the proposed analytical methodologies showing appreciable score of 0.81. <bold>(b)</bold> Application of AGREE metric to assess the greenness of the reported analytical methodologies showing appreciable score of 0.69.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_13486_Fig10_HTML" id="MO10"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par82">Also, GAPI was applied which is a comprehensive visual tool used to assess the environmental sustainability of analytical procedures throughout all stages of method execution from sample collection to final analysis. Unlike other tools that offer a single numerical score, GAPI evaluates the method through a stepwise breakdown of 15 specific criteria spread across five key domains: sample handling, reagents and solvents, instrumentation, waste management, and occupational safety<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. Each parameter is independently assessed and color-coded: green denotes low environmental impact, yellow indicates a moderate burden, and red signals a high or undesirable effect. These assessments are displayed in a hexagonal pictogram, which offers a clear visual summary of the method&#x02019;s overall greenness. The dominance of green fields in the chart reflects a well-aligned method with sustainable practices, while red areas point to potential areas for environmental improvement.</p><p id="Par83">To construct the GAPI profile, each component of the analytical method is carefully analyzed based on green chemistry criteria, and the corresponding colors are assigned to the relevant sections of the pictogram. Although GAPI does not produce a single final score, the visual distribution of colors offers a powerful, semi-quantitative measure of a method&#x02019;s sustainability performance.</p><p id="Par84">In our current study, the GAPI pictogram for the proposed methods (Fig. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>a) demonstrated a strong green profile with minimal red zones, confirming the method&#x02019;s alignment with environmentally friendly practices. The use of safe solvents, reduced chemical consumption, simplified sample preparation, and low waste output all contributed to this favorable evaluation. When compared to the reported method (<bold>(</bold>Fig. <xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref>b), which showed more environmental weaknesses, our proposed approach proved to be significantly more sustainable. This clearly positions the developed method as a completely green and eco-friendly alternative, offering a superior choice for modern pharmaceutical analysis in line with green chemistry objectives.</p><p id="Par85">
<fig id="Fig11"><label>Fig. 11</label><caption><p><bold>(a)</bold> Application of GAPI metric to assess the greenness of the proposed analytical methodologies showing appreciable greenness outcomes as shown on the color code of the pictograms. <bold>(b) A</bold>pplication of the GAPI metric to assess the greenness of the reported analytical methodologies reveals the summarized greenness outcomes, as indicated by the color-coded pictograms, in comparison with the proposed methodologies.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_13486_Fig11_HTML" id="MO11"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par86">Integrating the GbD approach into the development of analytical methods significantly enhances outcomes on both the AGREE and GAPI scales. By embedding sustainability principles from the outset, researchers can prioritize environmentally friendly practices and materials, leading to greater efficiency and reduced environmental impact. This proactive strategy not only fosters innovation in analytical methodologies but also supports the advancement of sustainable practices within the field by minimizing energy consumption, reducing solvent use, and selecting safer, less toxic reagents.</p></sec><sec id="Sec103"><title>Validation</title><p id="Par87">Validation of the analytical methods was conducted in accordance with the International Conference on Harmonization (ICH) Q2 (R1) guidelines<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup> encompassing key parameters such as linearity, limit of detection (LOD), limit of quantitation (LOQ), selectivity, accuracy, and precision.</p><sec id="Sec26"><title>Linearity, limit of detection (LOD), and limit of quantitation (LOQ)</title><p id="Par88">The linearity of the developed spectrophotometric methods for HCTZ and TRIM was assessed by measuring concentrations within the ranges specified in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The results demonstrated robust linearity, characterized by high coefficients of determination and minimal percentage relative standard deviation (% RSD). Each concentration was analyzed in triplicate, and the corresponding regression equations were computed, as detailed in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p><p id="Par89">The LOD and LOQ were established by determining the lowest concentrations that could be reliably detected and quantified, respectively, following the ICH Q2 (R1) recommendation, as outlined in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec27"><title>Accuracy</title><p id="Par90">The accuracy of the proposed methodologies was evaluated by comparing the measured concentrations of the target compounds with their known values, expressed as mean percentage recoveries presented in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Further validation was achieved through the standard addition technique, where known quantities of HCTZ and TRIM were spiked into pre-analyzed samples at three distinct concentration levels. The results indicated no interference from excipients, as shown in Table <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>.</p><p id="Par91">
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Application of standard addition technique using the proposed spectrophotometric methods:.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Drug</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Pharmaceutical taken (&#x000b5;g/ml)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Pure added (&#x000b5;g/ml)</th><th align="left" colspan="5">Pharmaceutical found <sup>a</sup> (&#x000b5;g/ml)</th><th align="left" colspan="5">Recovery <sup>b</sup> (%R)</th></tr><tr><th align="left">FSD</th><th align="left">ISM</th><th align="left">ACM</th><th align="left">RDF</th><th align="left">RDM</th><th align="left">FSD</th><th align="left">ISM</th><th align="left">ACM</th><th align="left">RDF</th><th align="left">RDM</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">HCTZ</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">4</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">3.983</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">3.978</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">3.995</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">4.009</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">4.035</td><td align="left">99.18</td><td align="left">100.77</td><td align="left">99.89</td><td align="left">100.95</td><td align="left">100.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">98.28</td><td align="left">101.49</td><td align="left">98.31</td><td align="left">99.98</td><td align="left">99.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">100.13</td><td align="left">99.77</td><td align="left">99.32</td><td align="left">101.12</td><td align="left">100.98</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">Mean &#x000b1; %RSD</td><td align="left">99.19&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.934</td><td align="left">100.68&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.857</td><td align="left">99.17&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.805</td><td align="left"><p>100.68 &#x000b1;</p><p>0.615</p></td><td align="left"><p>100.47&#x000b1;</p><p>0.500</p></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="4">TRIM</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">6</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">6.035</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">5.978</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">5.978</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">6.005</td><td align="left" rowspan="3">6.052</td><td align="left">101.85</td><td align="left">101.19</td><td align="left">101.19</td><td align="left">100.76</td><td align="left">100.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">102.62</td><td align="left">101.42</td><td align="left">101.42</td><td align="left">101.23</td><td align="left">100.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">101.89</td><td align="left">101.23</td><td align="left">101.23</td><td align="left">99.92</td><td align="left">99.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="7">Mean &#x000b1; %RSD</td><td align="left">102.12&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.425</td><td align="left">101.28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.120</td><td align="left">101.28&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.120</td><td align="left"><p>100.64 &#x000b1;</p><p>0.664</p></td><td align="left"><p>100.07 &#x000b1;</p><p>0.544</p></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup> average of three determinations.</p><p><sup>b</sup> average of three determination.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec28"><title>Precision</title><p id="Par92">The precision of the proposed methods was assessed through both repeatability and intermediate precision, as illustrated in Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec29"><title>Repeatability</title><p id="Par93">For repeatability assessment, three different concentrations of HCTZ and TRIM were analyzed in triplicate on the same day. The percentage relative standard deviation (% RSD) was subsequently calculated.</p></sec><sec id="Sec30"><title>Intermediate precision</title><p id="Par94">To evaluate intermediate precision, the same concentrations used for repeatability were analyzed three times over three consecutive days. The % RSD was calculated to assess variability between days.</p></sec><sec id="Sec31"><title>Selectivity</title><p id="Par95">The selectivity of the proposed methods was evaluated by analyzing laboratory-prepared mixtures containing varying ratios of HCTZ and TRIM. The mean recovery percentage (% R) and the standard deviation (SD) were calculated and are presented in Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec105"><title>Comparative statistical assessment</title><p id="Par96">The recoveries of each of the proposed methods were compared statistically against the reported method<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> using student t-test and F-test and the results are shown in Table <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. The results reveal that the calculated student t-test and F-test values were less than their critical values indicating that there was no significant statistical difference between each of the proposed sensors and the reported method. Statistical evaluation of the results and effect sizes (Eta squared) of the assays were conducted using a one-way ANOVA test at a 95% confidence interval. The results from the ANOVA test indicated that the variability in the results can be attributed to the differences among the methods. However, the analysis revealed no statistically significant difference between the proposed methods and the reference method, as shown in Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>.</p><p id="Par97">
<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>One-Way ANOVA statistical analysis with a 95% confidence interval on recovery percentage data from GbD-Based spectrophotometric methods applied to Maxzide<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> tablets.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Source of variation</th><th align="left">Sum of squares</th><th align="left">Degrees of freedom</th><th align="left">Mean square</th><th align="left">F-value</th><th align="left">P-value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="6">HCTZ</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Between groups</td><td align="left">5.99</td><td align="left">3.00</td><td align="left">2.00</td><td align="left">1.16 <sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Within groups</td><td align="left">13.82</td><td align="left">8.00</td><td align="left">1.73</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Total</td><td align="left">19.81</td><td align="left">11.00</td><td align="left"><bold><italic>&#x003b7;</italic></bold>
<sup><bold>2 b</bold></sup></td><td align="left">0.30</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6">TRIM</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Between groups</td><td align="left">8.29</td><td align="left">3.00</td><td align="left">2.76</td><td align="left">2.36 <sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Within groups</td><td align="left">9.35</td><td align="left">8.00</td><td align="left">1.17</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Total</td><td align="left">17.64</td><td align="left">11.00</td><td align="left"><bold><italic>&#x003b7;</italic></bold>
<sup><bold>2 b</bold></sup></td><td align="left">0.47</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup> The F-critical value for HCTZ and TRIM was 4.07.</p><p><sup>b</sup> Eta squared values indicating the magnitude of variability in the results that can be attributed to the differences among the methods.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec33"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par98">Here in, we successfully demonstrated the effectiveness of the GbD approach in developing UV spectrophotometric methodologies capable of simultaneously quantifying HCTZ and TRIM in both dosage forms and laboratory prepared mixtures. The methods developed included simple mathematical techniques such as Fourier Self-Deconvolution, Absorption correction method, and Isoabsorptive point method, alongside universal ratio spectra-based approaches like ratio difference and ratio derivative methods. By assimilating in-silico techniques such as MD and TD-DFT electronic dynamics simulations with UV spectroscopy, we gained valuable insights into solute-solvent interactions at both molecular and quantum levels. The GbD framework facilitated the selection of the optimal solvent system, characterized by minimal interactions with the solute, which in turn reduced peak broadening and spectral interference. This premeditated decision not only made method development easier by requiring less analytical work, but it also improved environmental sustainability by using less energy and producing less waste. While the ratio-based approaches improved quantification&#x02019;s sensitivity and specificity, the straightforward mathematical techniques used offered several benefits, such as resilience and simplicity of use. These approaches&#x02019; dependability and interchangeability were confirmed by statistical comparisons that showed no discernible differences between them. Overall, as shown by the excellent results on the GAPI and AGREE greenness scales, the use of the GbD approach in our methodology demonstrates the potential for creative and sustainable practices in analytical chemistry. This accomplishment opens the door to more effective and sustainable analytical methods. Moreover, the proposed methodologies are not only simple and sustainable but also serve as effective alternatives to chromatographic techniques for routine analytical methods in quality control laboratories, especially in limited resources regions. Their ease of use requires minimal training, and they provide enhanced occupational safety, making them particularly advantageous in these settings.</p></sec><sec id="Sec34" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2025_13486_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>A.E: Conceptualization, Methodology, Data collection, Data analysis, writing original draft. K.A: Conceptualization, Methodology, Data collection, Data analysis, writing original draft. E.D: Conceptualization, Methodology, Data collection, Data analysis, Reviewing and editing.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &#x00026; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB). This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>The datasets generated during and/or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes><title>Declarations</title><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par99">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Epicoco</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oltra</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Saint Jean</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Knowledge dynamics and sources of eco-innovation: mapping the green chemistry community</article-title><source>Technol. Forecast. Soc. Change</source><year>2014</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>388</fpage><lpage>402</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Epicoco, M., Oltra, V. &#x00026; Saint Jean, M. Knowledge dynamics and sources of eco-innovation: mapping the green chemistry community. <italic>Technol. Forecast. Soc. Change</italic>. <bold>81</bold>, 388&#x02013;402 (2014).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miladinovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Green analytical chemistry: integrating sustainability into undergraduate education: green analytical chemistry: integrating sustainability into undergraduate education: S. Miladinovi&#x00107;</article-title><source>Anal. Bioanal Chem.</source><year>2024</year><volume>417</volume><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>673</lpage><?supplied-pmid 39641778?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39641778</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Miladinovi&#x00107;, S. M. Green analytical chemistry: integrating sustainability into undergraduate education: green analytical chemistry: integrating sustainability into undergraduate education: S. Miladinovi&#x00107;. <italic>Anal. Bioanal Chem.</italic><bold>417</bold>, 665&#x02013;673 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39641778</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thanoon</surname><given-names>ES</given-names></name><name><surname>Saeed</surname><given-names>AMA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of green spectrophotometric method for determination of Metoclopramide hydrochloride</article-title><source>Egypt. J. Chem.</source><year>2021</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>3451</fpage><lpage>3456</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Thanoon, E. S. &#x00026; Saeed, A. M. A. Development of green spectrophotometric method for determination of Metoclopramide hydrochloride. <italic>Egypt. J. Chem.</italic><bold>64</bold>, 3451&#x02013;3456 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keith</surname><given-names>LH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gron</surname><given-names>LU</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Green analytical methodologies</article-title><source>Chem. Rev.</source><year>2007</year><volume>107</volume><fpage>2695</fpage><lpage>2708</lpage><?supplied-pmid 17521200?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17521200</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Keith, L. H., Gron, L. U. &#x00026; Young, J. L. Green analytical methodologies. <italic>Chem. Rev.</italic><bold>107</bold>, 2695&#x02013;2708 (2007).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17521200</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ra&#x0017e;i&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Arsenijevi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00110;ogo Mra&#x0010d;evi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Mu&#x00161;ovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Trti&#x00107;-Petrovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Greener chemistry in analytical sciences: from green solvents to applications in complex matrices. Current challenges and future perspectives: a critical review</article-title><source>Analyst</source><year>2023</year><volume>148</volume><fpage>3130</fpage><lpage>3152</lpage><?supplied-pmid 37337738?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37337738</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Ra&#x0017e;i&#x00107;, S., Arsenijevi&#x00107;, J., &#x00110;ogo Mra&#x0010d;evi&#x00107;, S., Mu&#x00161;ovi&#x00107;, J. &#x00026; Trti&#x00107;-Petrovi&#x00107;, T. Greener chemistry in analytical sciences: from green solvents to applications in complex matrices. Current challenges and future perspectives: a critical review. <italic>Analyst</italic><bold>148</bold>, 3130&#x02013;3152 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37337738</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdelshakour</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Greenness-by-design approach for developing novel UV spectrophotometric methodologies resolving a quaternary overlapping mixture</article-title><source>Arch. Pharm. (Weinheim)</source><year>2023</year><volume>356</volume><fpage>e2300216</fpage><?supplied-pmid 37276368?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37276368</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Abdelshakour, M. A. et al. Greenness-by-design approach for developing novel UV spectrophotometric methodologies resolving a quaternary overlapping mixture. <italic>Arch. Pharm. (Weinheim)</italic>. <bold>356</bold>, e2300216 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37276368</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Eissa, S. M. et al. Ecological spectroscopic methodologies for quantifying co-administered drugs in human plasma by photochemical quantum mechanical simulation. <italic>Heliyon</italic><bold>10</bold>, e24466 (2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Using MD simulations to calculate how solvents modulate solubility</article-title><source>J. Chem. Theory Comput.</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>1930</fpage><lpage>1941</lpage><?supplied-pmid 26878198?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26878198</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Liu, S. et al. Using MD simulations to calculate how solvents modulate solubility. <italic>J. Chem. Theory Comput.</italic><bold>12</bold>, 1930&#x02013;1941 (2016).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26878198</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scheid</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Remy</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name><name><surname>Leb&#x000e8;gue</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Malinowski</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mangin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Light induced ultrafast magnetization dynamics in metallic compounds</article-title><source>J. Magn. Magn. Mater.</source><year>2022</year><volume>560</volume><fpage>169596</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Scheid, P., Remy, Q., Leb&#x000e8;gue, S., Malinowski, G. &#x00026; Mangin, S. Light induced ultrafast magnetization dynamics in metallic compounds. <italic>J. Magn. Magn. Mater.</italic><bold>560</bold>, 169596 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Col&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Aguilar</surname><given-names>M&#x000c1;</given-names></name><name><surname>Mart&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A theoretical study of solvent effects on the structure and UV-vis spectroscopy of 3-Hydroxyflavone (3-HF) and some simplified molecular models</article-title><source>ACS Omega</source><year>2023</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>19939</fpage><lpage>19949</lpage><?supplied-pmid 37305262?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37305262</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Col&#x000ed;n, M. J., Aguilar, M. &#x000c1;. &#x00026; Mart&#x000ed;n, M. E. A theoretical study of solvent effects on the structure and UV-vis spectroscopy of 3-Hydroxyflavone (3-HF) and some simplified molecular models. <italic>ACS Omega</italic>. <bold>8</bold>, 19939&#x02013;19949 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37305262</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roszak</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Maciejewski</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Katrusiak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Krystkowiak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Solute&#x02009;&#x02013;&#x02009;solvent repulsion effects on the absorption spectra of anthracene in n-hexane investigated under high pressure</article-title><source>Spectrochim Acta - Part. Mol. Biomol. Spectrosc.</source><year>2023</year><volume>299</volume><fpage>122822</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Roszak, K., Maciejewski, A., Katrusiak, A. &#x00026; Krystkowiak, E. Solute&#x02009;&#x02013;&#x02009;solvent repulsion effects on the absorption spectra of anthracene in n-hexane investigated under high pressure. <italic>Spectrochim Acta - Part. Mol. Biomol. Spectrosc.</italic><bold>299</bold>, 122822 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">OConnor, T. &#x00026; Lee, S. Emerging technology for modernizing pharmaceutical production: Continuous manufacturing. in <italic>Developing Solid Oral Dosage Forms: Pharmaceutical Theory and Practice: Second Edition</italic> (eds. Qiu, Y., Chen, Y., Zhang, G. G. Z., Yu, L. &#x00026; Mantri, R. V. B. T.-D. S. O. D. F. (Second E.) 1031&#x02013;1046Academic Press, (2017). 10.1016/B978-0-12-802447-8.00037-6</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tushar, C. &#x00026; Okusa, M. D. Aldosterone Antagonists, Amiloride, and Triamterene. in <italic>Critical Care Nephrology: Third Edition</italic> (eds. Ronco, C., Bellomo, R., Kellum, J. A. &#x00026; Ricci, Z. B. T.-C. C. N. (Third E.) 368&#x02013;373Elsevier, (2017). 10.1016/B978-0-323-44942-7.00063-7</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bonagura, J. D., Schober, K. E. &#x00026; Saunders, P. Chapter 146 - Cardiovascular Drugs. in (. Birchard, S. J.Sherding, R. G. B. T.-S. M. of S. A. (2006). 10.1016/B0-72-160422-6/50148-0</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR15" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stolarczyk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Apola</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Krzek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lech</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous determination of triamterene and Hydrochlorothiazide in tablets using derivative spectrophotometry</article-title><source>Acta Pol. Pharm. - Drug Res.</source><year>2008</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>283</fpage><lpage>287</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR15" publication-type="journal">Stolarczyk, M., Apola, A., Krzek, J. &#x00026; Lech, K. Simultaneous determination of triamterene and Hydrochlorothiazide in tablets using derivative spectrophotometry. <italic>Acta Pol. Pharm. - Drug Res.</italic><bold>65</bold>, 283&#x02013;287 (2008).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kargosha</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sarrafi</surname><given-names>AHM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spectrophotometric simultaneous determination of triamterene and Hydrochlorothiazide in Triamterene-H tablets by multivariate calibration methods</article-title><source>J. Pharm. Biomed. Anal.</source><year>2001</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>273</fpage><lpage>279</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11470204?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11470204</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Kargosha, K. &#x00026; Sarrafi, A. H. M. Spectrophotometric simultaneous determination of triamterene and Hydrochlorothiazide in Triamterene-H tablets by multivariate calibration methods. <italic>J. Pharm. Biomed. Anal.</italic><bold>26</bold>, 273&#x02013;279 (2001).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11470204</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Antakli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nejem</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Kullah</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analytical spectrophotometric study for determining Hydrocholrothiazide individually or with combination with triametrene in some pharmaceutical formulations</article-title><source>Res. J. Pharm. Technol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2351</fpage><lpage>2356</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Antakli, S., Nejem, L. &#x00026; Kullah, A. Analytical spectrophotometric study for determining Hydrocholrothiazide individually or with combination with triametrene in some pharmaceutical formulations. <italic>Res. J. Pharm. Technol.</italic><bold>11</bold>, 2351&#x02013;2356 (2018).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mohammadpour</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sohrabi</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Jourabchi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Continuous wavelet and derivative transform applied to the overlapping spectra for the quantitative spectrophotometric multi-resolution of triamterene and Hydrochlorothiazide in triamterene-H tablets</article-title><source>Talanta</source><year>2010</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>1821</fpage><lpage>1825</lpage><?supplied-pmid 20441980?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20441980</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Mohammadpour, K., Sohrabi, M. R. &#x00026; Jourabchi, A. Continuous wavelet and derivative transform applied to the overlapping spectra for the quantitative spectrophotometric multi-resolution of triamterene and Hydrochlorothiazide in triamterene-H tablets. <italic>Talanta</italic><bold>81</bold>, 1821&#x02013;1825 (2010).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20441980</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ma&#x0015b;lanka</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Krzek</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stolarczyk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous analysis of hydrochlorothiazide, triamterene, furosemide, and spironolactone by densitometric TLC</article-title><source>J. Planar Chromatogr. - Mod. TLC</source><year>2009</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>410</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Ma&#x0015b;lanka, A., Krzek, J. &#x00026; Stolarczyk, M. Simultaneous analysis of hydrochlorothiazide, triamterene, furosemide, and spironolactone by densitometric TLC. <italic>J. Planar Chromatogr. - Mod. TLC</italic>. <bold>22</bold>, 405&#x02013;410 (2009).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR20" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Margaryan</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikayelyan</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Zakaryan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Armoudjian</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Alaverdyan</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous determination of triamterene and Hydrochlorothiazide in human plasma by liquid chromatography tandem mass spectrometry and its application to a bioequivalence study</article-title><source>SN Appl. Sci.</source><year>2019</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR20" publication-type="journal">Margaryan, T., Mikayelyan, A., Zakaryan, H., Armoudjian, Y. &#x00026; Alaverdyan, H. Simultaneous determination of triamterene and Hydrochlorothiazide in human plasma by liquid chromatography tandem mass spectrometry and its application to a bioequivalence study. <italic>SN Appl. Sci.</italic><bold>1</bold>, 1&#x02013;11 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Simultaneous determination of Hydrochlorothiazide and triamterene in capsule formulations by High-Performance liquid chromatography</article-title><source>J. Pharm. Sci.</source><year>1981</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>1083</fpage><lpage>1085</lpage><?supplied-pmid 6101161?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6101161</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Menon, G. N. &#x00026; White, L. B. Simultaneous determination of Hydrochlorothiazide and triamterene in capsule formulations by High-Performance liquid chromatography. <italic>J. Pharm. Sci.</italic><bold>70</bold>, 1083&#x02013;1085 (1981).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6101161</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Siddiqui</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>AlOthman</surname><given-names>ZA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analytical techniques in pharmaceutical analysis: A review</article-title><source>Arab. J. Chem.</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>S1409</fpage><lpage>S1421</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Siddiqui, M. R., AlOthman, Z. A. &#x00026; Rahman, N. Analytical techniques in pharmaceutical analysis: A review. <italic>Arab. J. Chem.</italic><bold>10</bold>, S1409&#x02013;S1421 (2017).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Kinetic spectrophotometric method for the determination of Perindopril erbumine in pure and commercial dosage forms</article-title><source>Arab. J. Chem.</source><year>2017</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>S831</fpage><lpage>S838</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Rahman, N., Rahman, H. &#x00026; Haque, S. M. Kinetic spectrophotometric method for the determination of Perindopril erbumine in pure and commercial dosage forms. <italic>Arab. J. Chem.</italic><bold>10</bold>, S831&#x02013;S838 (2017).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Al-Shatti, B. J. &#x00026; Alsairafi, Z. &#x00026; Al-Tannak, N. F. Green chemistry and its implementation in pharmaceutical analysis. <italic>Rev Anal. Chem</italic><bold>42</bold>, 20230069 (2023).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR25" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>SKM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Box&#x02013;Behnken experimental design for optimizing the HPLC method to determine Hydrochlorothiazide in pharmaceutical formulations and biological fluid</article-title><source>J. Mol. Liq</source><year>2022</year><volume>352</volume><fpage>118708</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR25" publication-type="journal">Haque, S. K. M. Box&#x02013;Behnken experimental design for optimizing the HPLC method to determine Hydrochlorothiazide in pharmaceutical formulations and biological fluid. <italic>J. Mol. Liq</italic>. <bold>352</bold>, 118708 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR26" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azmi</surname><given-names>SNH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Box&#x02013;Behnken design based development of UV-reversed phase high performance liquid chromatographic method for determination of ascorbic acid in tablet formulations</article-title><source>Separations</source><year>2022</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>361</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR26" publication-type="journal">Azmi, S. N. H. et al. Box&#x02013;Behnken design based development of UV-reversed phase high performance liquid chromatographic method for determination of ascorbic acid in tablet formulations. <italic>Separations</italic><bold>9</bold>, 361 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR27" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Application of Box&#x02013;Behnken design combined response surface methodology to optimize HPLC and spectrophotometric techniques for quantifying febuxostat in pharmaceutical formulations and spiked wastewater samples</article-title><source>Microchem J.</source><year>2023</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>108191</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR27" publication-type="journal">Haque, S. M. et al. Application of Box&#x02013;Behnken design combined response surface methodology to optimize HPLC and spectrophotometric techniques for quantifying febuxostat in pharmaceutical formulations and spiked wastewater samples. <italic>Microchem J.</italic><bold>184</bold>, 108191 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR28" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaaban</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ecological impact of liquid chromatographic methods reported for bioanalysis of COVID-19 drug, hydroxychloroquine: insights on greenness assessment</article-title><source>Microchem J.</source><year>2023</year><volume>184</volume><fpage>108145</fpage><?supplied-pmid 36404889?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36404889</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR28" publication-type="journal">Shaaban, H. The ecological impact of liquid chromatographic methods reported for bioanalysis of COVID-19 drug, hydroxychloroquine: insights on greenness assessment. <italic>Microchem J.</italic><bold>184</bold>, 108145 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">36404889</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR29" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neese</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Software update: the ORCA program system&#x02014;Version 5.0</article-title><source>Wiley Interdiscip Rev. Comput. Mol. Sci.</source><year>2022</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e1606</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR29" publication-type="journal">Neese, F. Software update: the ORCA program system&#x02014;Version 5.0. <italic>Wiley Interdiscip Rev. Comput. Mol. Sci.</italic><bold>12</bold>, e1606 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Molecular Operating Environment (MOE) &#x00026; 2R7. 10 Chemical Computing Group ULC, 1010 Sherbooke St. West, Suite #910, Montreal, QC, Canada, H. Molecular Operating Environment (MOE), 2015.10 Chemical Computing Group ULC, 1010 Sherbooke St. West, Suite #910, Montreal, QC, Canada, H3A 2R7,. at (2015). <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.chemcomp.com/en/index.htm">https://www.chemcomp.com/en/index.htm</ext-link> (2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tobergte, D. R. &#x00026; Curtis, S. MOE Molecular Operating Environment. <italic>Journal of Chemical Information and Modeling</italic> vol. 53 at (2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR32" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petrenko</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kossmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Neese</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficient time-dependent density functional theory approximations for hybrid density functionals: analytical gradients and parallelization</article-title><source>J. Chem. Phys.</source><year>2011</year><volume>134</volume><fpage>54116</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR32" publication-type="journal">Petrenko, T., Kossmann, S. &#x00026; Neese, F. Efficient time-dependent density functional theory approximations for hybrid density functionals: analytical gradients and parallelization. <italic>J. Chem. Phys.</italic><bold>134</bold>, 54116 (2011).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR33" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mostafa</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Miniaturized chip integrated ecological sensor for the quantitation of Milnacipran hydrochloride in the presence of its impurities in dosage form and human plasma</article-title><source>J. Electrochem. Soc.</source><year>2023</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>087504</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR33" publication-type="journal">Mostafa, A. E. et al. Miniaturized chip integrated ecological sensor for the quantitation of Milnacipran hydrochloride in the presence of its impurities in dosage form and human plasma. <italic>J. Electrochem. Soc.</italic><bold>170</bold>, 087504 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Ahmed, S., Mustaan, N., Sheraz, M. A. &#x00026; Nabi, S. A. A. un &#x00026; Ahmad, I. Validation of a UV Spectrometric Method for the Assay of Tolfenamic Acid in Organic Solvents. <italic>J. Pharm.</italic> 1&#x02013;8 (2015). (2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhao, L., Ma, K. &#x00026; Yang, Z. Changes of water hydrogen bond network with different externalities. <italic>International Journal of Molecular Sciences</italic> vol. 16 8454&#x02013;8489 at (2015). 10.3390/ijms16048454</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR36" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azizi</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Chaichi</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Yousefi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Investigation of solvent effects on UV-vis absorption spectra of dihydroxybenzene derivatives by solvatochromic parameters</article-title><source>Spectrochim Acta - Part. Mol. Biomol. Spectrosc.</source><year>2009</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>105</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR36" publication-type="journal">Azizi, S. N., Chaichi, M. J. &#x00026; Yousefi, M. Investigation of solvent effects on UV-vis absorption spectra of dihydroxybenzene derivatives by solvatochromic parameters. <italic>Spectrochim Acta - Part. Mol. Biomol. Spectrosc.</italic><bold>73</bold>, 101&#x02013;105 (2009).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR37" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peintinger</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Bredow</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Consistent Gaussian basis sets of triple-zeta Valence with polarization quality for solid-state calculations</article-title><source>J. Comput. Chem.</source><year>2013</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>459</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23115105?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23115105</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR37" publication-type="journal">Peintinger, M. F., Oliveira, D. V. &#x00026; Bredow, T. Consistent Gaussian basis sets of triple-zeta Valence with polarization quality for solid-state calculations. <italic>J. Comput. Chem.</italic><bold>34</bold>, 451&#x02013;459 (2013).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23115105</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR38" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sherefedin</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Investigating the effects of solvent Polarity and temperature on the molecular, photophysical, and thermodynamic properties of sinapic acid using DFT and TDDFT</article-title><source>RSC Adv.</source><year>2024</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>23364</fpage><lpage>23377</lpage><?supplied-pmid 39049890?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39049890</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR38" publication-type="journal">Sherefedin, U. et al. Investigating the effects of solvent Polarity and temperature on the molecular, photophysical, and thermodynamic properties of sinapic acid using DFT and TDDFT. <italic>RSC Adv.</italic><bold>14</bold>, 23364&#x02013;23377 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39049890</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Lapedes, A. <italic>Molecular Driving Forces: Statistical Thermodynamics in Chemistry and Biology. Briefings in Bioinformatics</italic>vol. 4 (Garland Science, 2003).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">El-Henawee, M. M., El-Hay, A., Attala, S. S. &#x00026; Eissa, M. S. K. Smart UV spectrophotometric methods based on simple mathematical filtration and classical methods for the simultaneous determination of Tamsulosin and solifenacin: A comparative study of efficacy and spectral resolution. <italic>Spectrochim Acta - Part. Mol. Biomol. Spectrosc</italic><bold>247</bold>, 118853 (2021).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR41" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elsonbaty</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Attala</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An eco-friendly modified methodology for the resolution of binary pharmaceutical mixtures based on self-deconvolution of the UV spectrophotometric spectra in the fourier domain: application of fourier self-deconvolution in UV spectroscopy</article-title><source>Spectrochim Acta - Part. Mol. Biomol. Spectrosc.</source><year>2022</year><volume>264</volume><fpage>120262</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR41" publication-type="journal">Elsonbaty, A. &#x00026; Attala, K. An eco-friendly modified methodology for the resolution of binary pharmaceutical mixtures based on self-deconvolution of the UV spectrophotometric spectra in the fourier domain: application of fourier self-deconvolution in UV spectroscopy. <italic>Spectrochim Acta - Part. Mol. Biomol. Spectrosc.</italic><bold>264</bold>, 120262 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR42" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Attala</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Elsonbaty</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advanced eco-friendly UV spectrophotometric approach for resolving overlapped spectral signals of antihypertensive agents in their binary and tertiary pharmaceutical dosage form</article-title><source>Spectrochim Acta Part. Mol. Biomol. Spectrosc.</source><year>2021</year><volume>258</volume><fpage>119855</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR42" publication-type="journal">Attala, K. &#x00026; Elsonbaty, A. Advanced eco-friendly UV spectrophotometric approach for resolving overlapped spectral signals of antihypertensive agents in their binary and tertiary pharmaceutical dosage form. <italic>Spectrochim Acta Part. Mol. Biomol. Spectrosc.</italic><bold>258</bold>, 119855 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR43" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>El-Hanboushy</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marzouk</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fayez</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdelkawy</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lotfy</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sustainable spectrophotometric determination of antihypertensive medicines reducing COVID-19 risk via paired wavelength data processing technique - Assessment of purity, greenness and whiteness</article-title><source>Sustain. Chem. Pharm.</source><year>2022</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>100806</fpage><?supplied-pmid 35992213?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35992213</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR43" publication-type="journal">El-Hanboushy, S., Marzouk, H. M., Fayez, Y. M., Abdelkawy, M. &#x00026; Lotfy, H. M. Sustainable spectrophotometric determination of antihypertensive medicines reducing COVID-19 risk via paired wavelength data processing technique - Assessment of purity, greenness and whiteness. <italic>Sustain. Chem. Pharm.</italic><bold>29</bold>, 100806 (2022).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">35992213</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR44" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kauppinen</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name><name><surname>Moffatt</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mantsch</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fourier Self-Deconvolution: A method for resolving intrinsically overlapped bands</article-title><source>Appl. Spectrosc.</source><year>1981</year><volume>35</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>276</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR44" publication-type="journal">Kauppinen, J. K., Moffatt, D. J., Mantsch, H. H. &#x00026; Cameron, D. G. Fourier Self-Deconvolution: A method for resolving intrinsically overlapped bands. <italic>Appl. Spectrosc.</italic><bold>35</bold>, 271&#x02013;276 (1981).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR45" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Abdelshakour</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Eco-Friendly UV-Spectrophotometric methods employing magnetic Nano-Composite polymer for the extraction and analysis of sexual boosters in adulterated food products: application of Computer-Aided design</article-title><source>J. AOAC Int.</source><year>2023</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>1608</fpage><lpage>1619</lpage><?supplied-pmid 37449906?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37449906</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR45" publication-type="journal">Abdelshakour, M. A. et al. Eco-Friendly UV-Spectrophotometric methods employing magnetic Nano-Composite polymer for the extraction and analysis of sexual boosters in adulterated food products: application of Computer-Aided design. <italic>J. AOAC Int.</italic><bold>106</bold>, 1608&#x02013;1619 (2023).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">37449906</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR46" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Darweish</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Marzouk</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fayez</surname><given-names>YM</given-names></name><name><surname>Eissa</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advanced spectrophotometric resolution techniques for a spectrally overlapping spasmolytic binary mixture along with Dichloroaniline as a toxic impurity: application to content uniformity testing</article-title><source>J. AOAC Int.</source><year>2023</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>25</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR46" publication-type="journal">Darweish, E., Marzouk, H. M., Fayez, Y. M. &#x00026; Eissa, M. S. Advanced spectrophotometric resolution techniques for a spectrally overlapping spasmolytic binary mixture along with Dichloroaniline as a toxic impurity: application to content uniformity testing. <italic>J. AOAC Int.</italic><bold>106</bold>, 14&#x02013;25 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR47" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elsonbaty</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Eissa</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassan</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdulwahab</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Separation-free spectrophotometric platforms for rapid assessment of combined antiplatelet therapy in complex matrices</article-title><source>Bioanalysis</source><year>2020</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>335</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><?supplied-pmid 32186937?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32186937</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR47" publication-type="journal">Elsonbaty, A., Eissa, M. S., Hassan, W. S. &#x00026; Abdulwahab, S. Separation-free spectrophotometric platforms for rapid assessment of combined antiplatelet therapy in complex matrices. <italic>Bioanalysis</italic><bold>12</bold>, 335&#x02013;348 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32186937</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR48" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Attala</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>In-silico analytical chemistry contributions to analytical and bio-analytical applications in spectroscopic and chromatographic techniques: molecular mechanical and quantum insights</article-title><source>Rec Pharm. Biomed. Sci.</source><year>2023</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>144</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR48" publication-type="journal">Attala, K. et al. In-silico analytical chemistry contributions to analytical and bio-analytical applications in spectroscopic and chromatographic techniques: molecular mechanical and quantum insights. <italic>Rec Pharm. Biomed. Sci.</italic><bold>7</bold>, 125&#x02013;144 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR49" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eissa</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Darweish</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Insights on ecological spectroscopic techniques recently adopted for pharmaceutical analysis: a comprehensive review from the perspective of greenness assessment metrics systems application</article-title><source>TrAC Trends Anal. Chem.</source><year>2024</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>117435</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR49" publication-type="journal">Eissa, M. S. &#x00026; Darweish, E. Insights on ecological spectroscopic techniques recently adopted for pharmaceutical analysis: a comprehensive review from the perspective of greenness assessment metrics systems application. <italic>TrAC Trends Anal. Chem.</italic><bold>170</bold>, 117435 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR50" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Elsonbaty</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Madkour</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Raoof</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abdel-Monem</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Attar</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>M. M. Computational design for eco-friendly visible spectrophotometric platform used for the assay of the antiviral agent in pharmaceutical dosage form</article-title><source>Spectrochim Acta Part. Mol. Biomol. Spectrosc.</source><year>2022</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>120897</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR50" publication-type="journal">Elsonbaty, A., Madkour, A. W., Abdel-Raoof, A. M., Abdel-Monem, A. H. &#x00026; El-Attar, A. A. M. M. Computational design for eco-friendly visible spectrophotometric platform used for the assay of the antiviral agent in pharmaceutical dosage form. <italic>Spectrochim Acta Part. Mol. Biomol. Spectrosc.</italic><bold>271</bold>, 120897 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR51" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>SKM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Greener high-performance liquid chromatography&#x02014;supported with computational studies to determine empagliflozin: box&#x02013;behnken design and Taguchi model for optimization</article-title><source>Arab. J. Sci. Eng.</source><year>2024</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>9667</fpage><lpage>9689</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR51" publication-type="journal">Haque, S. K. M. et al. Greener high-performance liquid chromatography&#x02014;supported with computational studies to determine empagliflozin: box&#x02013;behnken design and Taguchi model for optimization. <italic>Arab. J. Sci. Eng.</italic><bold>49</bold>, 9667&#x02013;9689 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR52" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haque</surname><given-names>SKM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abu-Judeh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jain</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabir</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Greener spectrophotometric and HPLC investigation of CNS agent pregabalin: Taguchi model and box-behnken design for method parameters optimization</article-title><source>J. Mol. Struct.</source><year>2024</year><volume>1317</volume><fpage>139143</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR52" publication-type="journal">Haque, S. K. M., Abu-Judeh, A., Jain, R. &#x00026; Kabir, A. Greener spectrophotometric and HPLC investigation of CNS agent pregabalin: Taguchi model and box-behnken design for method parameters optimization. <italic>J. Mol. Struct.</italic><bold>1317</bold>, 139143 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Haque, S. K. M. et al. Design of experiment (DoE), screening and optimization of system variables to develop and validate greener spectrophotometric investigation of repaglinide. <italic>Chem. Africa</italic><bold>7</bold>, 5225&#x02013;5243 (2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR54" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pena-Pereira</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Wojnowski</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Tobiszewski</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>AGREE - Analytical greenness metric approach and software</article-title><source>Anal. Chem.</source><year>2020</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>10076</fpage><lpage>10082</lpage><?supplied-pmid 32538619?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32538619</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR54" publication-type="journal">Pena-Pereira, F., Wojnowski, W. &#x00026; Tobiszewski, M. AGREE - Analytical greenness metric approach and software. <italic>Anal. Chem.</italic><bold>92</bold>, 10076&#x02013;10082 (2020).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">32538619</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR55" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x00142;otka-Wasylka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A new tool for the evaluation of the analytical procedure: green analytical procedure index</article-title><source>Talanta</source><year>2018</year><volume>181</volume><fpage>204</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><?supplied-pmid 29426502?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29426502</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR55" publication-type="journal">P&#x00142;otka-Wasylka, J. A new tool for the evaluation of the analytical procedure: green analytical procedure index. <italic>Talanta</italic><bold>181</bold>, 204&#x02013;209 (2018).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29426502</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Borman, P. &#x00026; Elder, D. Q2(R1) validation of analytical procedures. <italic>ICH Qual. Guidel</italic>. 127&#x02013;166. 10.1002/9781118971147.ch5 (2017).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>