<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta>
<article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">12635146</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">41266394</article-id>
<article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">23521</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-025-23521-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>SUSTAIN as a universal scoring tool for assessing sustainability development goals in African energy initiatives</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0847-4035</contrib-id><name><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>Fotouh R.</given-names></name><address><email>fotouhrashed@pharm.tanta.edu.eg</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7016-325X</contrib-id><name><surname>Bedair</surname><given-names>Alaa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/016jp5b92</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412258.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9477 7793</institution-id><institution>Pharmaceutical Analytical Chemistry Department, Faculty of Pharmacy, </institution><institution>Tanta University, </institution></institution-wrap>Tanta, 31111 Egypt </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/04gj69425</institution-id><institution>Medicinal Chemistry Department, </institution><institution>Faculty of Pharmacy, King Salman International University, </institution></institution-wrap>Ras Sudr, 46612 Egypt </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ROR">https://ror.org/05p2q6194</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.449877.1</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 4652 351X</institution-id><institution> Department of Analytical Chemistry, Faculty of Pharmacy, </institution><institution>University of Sadat City, </institution></institution-wrap>Sadat City, 32958 Egypt </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>20</day><month>11</month><year>2025</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2025</year></pub-date><volume>15</volume><elocation-id>40920</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>5</month><year>2025</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>7</day><month>10</month><year>2025</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2025</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2025</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbylicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Sustainability assessment has become an essential component of evaluating chemical methods and processes, requiring tools that deliver comprehensive and multi-dimensional evaluations. This manuscript introduces SUSTAIN, a novel and user-friendly tool designed to assess the sustainability of methods, processes and initiatives across environmental, social, and economic dimensions. Its core assessment framework is based on the 17 United Nations sustainable development goals (SDGs). By evaluating data related to key themes such as resource efficiency, energy use, emissions, waste generation, and social impact, and mapping this information onto the SDGs, SUSTAIN provides a dynamic platform to support informed decision-making for researchers, industry professionals, and policymakers. The tool uniquely evaluates the contribution to each of the United Nations&#x02019; SDGs, offering a structured analysis of their potential to advance or hinder global sustainability efforts. This paper presents the tool&#x02019;s conceptual framework, including its SDG-based assessment methodology, and illustrates its practical application through real-world examples, and freely available software (bit.ly/SUSTAIN2025). To demonstrate its versatility, SUSTAIN was applied to evaluate three major energy access initiatives: Power Africa, SE4All, and climate finance initiatives. The initiatives received normalized percentage scores of 50.00, 85.29, and 82.35, respectively, reflecting their overall alignment with the SDGs on a scale from 0 to 100. This quantitative comparison highlights the tool&#x02019;s utility in benchmarking sustainability performance and guiding strategic decision-making towards more sustainable development pathways.</p><sec><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>The online version contains supplementary material available at 10.1038/s41598-025-23521-x.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Sustainability</kwd><kwd>SUSTAIN</kwd><kwd>Application</kwd><kwd>SDG</kwd><kwd>Initiatives</kwd></kwd-group><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Energy science and technology</kwd><kwd>Engineering</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>Tanta University</institution></funding-source></award-group><open-access><p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &#x00026; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB).</p></open-access></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; Springer Nature Limited 2025</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par3">Sustainability has become an essential consideration in modern scientific and industrial practices, particularly within chemical methods and processes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. As the global community faces challenges such as climate change, resource depletion, and social inequalities, the need for sustainable practices has never been more urgent<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Chemical processes, due to their extensive use in various industries, have a profound impact on the environment, society, and economy<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. However, assessing the sustainability of these methods is complex and requires a multidimensional approach that considers environmental, social, and economic factors<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par4">Sustainability metrics serve as standardized metrics that measure the impact of processes on these three dimensions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. For example, metrics such as resource efficiency, energy consumption, emissions, and waste production provide insights into the environmental impact of chemical processes<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Social implications, such as health and safety, employment, and economic benefits, are equally crucial in this assessment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup>. This holistic evaluation enables stakeholders to make data-driven decisions that align with sustainable development goals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>. This manuscript introduces an innovative tool designed to assess the sustainability of methods, processes, projects and initiatives among others, highlighting its principles and application in relation to the United Nations&#x02019; SDGs. Each SDG will be discussed in detail, demonstrating how the tool evaluates the contribution of chemical processes to global sustainability efforts. To the best of our knowledge, this SDG-based holistic assessment has been not yet developed. The integration of sustainability metrics into a user-friendly tool offers a promising solution for simplifying the assessment process<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. By collecting and analyzing data from various sources, the tool can provide real-time feedback and generate visual representations of sustainability performance<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref></sup>. This facilitates the comparison of different approaches and identifies areas for improvement, promoting the adoption of greener practices<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methodology</title><p id="Par5">To ensure transparency and reproducibility, the methodology for applying the SUSTAIN tool is formally defined as follows.</p><sec id="Sec3"><title>Metric set and scoring rubric</title><p id="Par6">The SUSTAIN framework is built upon the 17 United Nations SDGs as its core set of sustainability metrics. Each SDG is assessed independently based on the documented impacts of the process or initiative under evaluation. The scoring rubric for each SDG is a five-point ordinal scale. A score of +&#x02009;2 (Strongly Fulfill) is assigned to an activity that directly and significantly advances the goal. A score of +&#x02009;1 (Fulfill) indicates the activity indirectly or moderately supports the goal. A score of 0 (Neutral) means the activity has no significant positive or negative impact; this category also serves for &#x0201c;Not Applicable&#x0201d; cases. A score of -1 (Violate) is given if the activity indirectly or moderately hinders the goal. Finally, a score of -2 (Strongly Violate) is reserved for an activity that directly and significantly undermines the goal. Detailed descriptions and examples for each score per SDG are provided in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>, which serves as the definitive guide for scoring.</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Data sources and scoring process</title><p id="Par7">The assessment is based on data extracted from literature and the official reports<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. The scoring was conducted by the authors of this study. Each author independently scored the three initiatives based on the criteria in (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The scores were then compared, and any discrepancies were discussed until a consensus was reached for each SDG score for each initiative.</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Calculation of the total SUSTAIN score</title><p id="Par8">Each SDG can contribute a maximum of 2 points to the total score, making the absolute maximum possible raw score 34 points for an initiative applicable to all 17 goals. If a specific SDG is deemed not applicable to the initiative or process under evaluation, it is assigned a score of 0. In this framework, not applicable SDGs are considered neutral: they neither increase nor decrease the score, but they also do not reduce the denominator. This ensures that methods, processes, and initiatives that contribute to a larger number of SDGs have more opportunity to achieve higher scores, thereby rewarding broader sustainability impact.</p><p id="Par9">To ensure fairness and comparability between initiatives of different scopes, a normalized percentage score is calculated as the percentage of the total points achieved out of the maximum possible score, which is 34.</p><p id="Par10">The SUSTAIN Score is calculated using the following formula:<disp-formula id="Equa"><tex-math id="d33e282">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\:\text{S}\text{U}\text{S}\text{T}\text{A}\text{I}\text{N}\:\text{S}\text{c}\text{o}\text{r}\text{e}\:\left(\text{\%}\right)\:=\frac{\left(\text{T}\text{o}\text{t}\text{a}\text{l}\:\text{p}\text{o}\text{i}\text{n}\text{t}\text{s}\:\text{s}\text{c}\text{o}\text{r}\text{e}\text{d}\right)}{\left(\text{M}\text{a}\text{x}\text{i}\text{m}\text{u}\text{m}\:\text{p}\text{o}\text{s}\text{s}\text{i}\text{b}\text{l}\text{e}\:\text{s}\text{c}\text{o}\text{r}\text{e}\right)}\times\:100$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula></p><p id="Par11">In this formula, total points scored is the sum of the scores across all 17 SDGs, with non-applicable goals contributing zero. The denominator, Maximum possible score, is set at 34 points (17 SDGs &#x000d7; 2 points each). This approach ensures that the final score consistently reflects performance relative to the absolute maximum, allowing for clear, reproducible, and transparent comparisons across diverse initiatives.</p><p id="Par12">Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> provides a comprehensive framework for assessing how a chemical process, product, or innovation aligns with the 17 United Nations SDGs. For each SDG, five levels of impact are defined: <italic>Strongly Fulfill</italic>, <italic>Fulfill</italic>, <italic>Neutral</italic>, <italic>Violate</italic>, and <italic>Strongly Violate</italic>. These categories represent the extent to which the assessed activity contributes to or detracts from the specific goal. Each category is supported by clear descriptions to aid in consistent evaluation. A numerical point system is used to quantify the assessment. If the total score is positive, the process overall supports the SDGs. A score of zero indicates a neutral impact, while a negative score suggests that the process violates or undermines the SDGs. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> presents four hypothetical scenarios illustrating varying degrees of sustainability performance based on the fulfillment of the 17 SDGs. In the first scenario (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a), all SDGs are strongly fulfilled, representing the optimal case of maximum sustainability impact, with fully green radials indicating strong alignment with each goal. The second scenario (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b) reflects a suboptimal or acceptable case in which some SDGs are strongly fulfilled (green radials), others are partially fulfilled (partially green radials), some are not applicable (yellow radials), and a few are either partially violated (partially red radials) or fully violated (red radials). Despite these variations, the overall SUSTAIN score remains positive, signifying that the initiative still contributes positively to sustainability. In the third scenario (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c), the total SUSTAIN score equals zero, indicating a balance between supporting and violating the SDGs. This neutral outcome highlights areas where improvements are needed, even though some goals may still be fully achieved. Finally, the fourth scenario (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d) illustrates a negative total score, suggesting that the initiative fails to support the SDGs meaningfully and may, in fact, hinder progress toward sustainability. This case highlights the inadequacy of current efforts and the need for significant re-evaluation and strategic redirection.</p><p id="Par13">
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Points system and examples of methods, processes, and initiatives and their impact on the different SDGs.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">SDG</th><th align="left">Category</th><th align="left">Description</th><th align="left">Points</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">SDG 1 (no poverty)</td><td align="left">Strongly fulfill</td><td align="left">Directly supports poverty eradication by promoting economic empowerment and improving access to essential resources.</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fulfill</td><td align="left">Indirectly contributes to poverty reduction by improving resource efficiency or creating employment opportunities.</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neutral</td><td align="left">No significant impact on poverty alleviation or economic inequality.</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Violate</td><td align="left">Contributes to poverty by harming livelihoods or reducing access to resources.</td><td align="left">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly violate</td><td align="left">Severely exacerbates poverty by destroying livelihoods or causing large-scale harm.</td><td align="left">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">SDG 2 (zero hunger)</td><td align="left">Strongly fulfill</td><td align="left">Directly enhances food security and sustainable agriculture.</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fulfill</td><td align="left">Indirectly contributes to food security and sustainable agriculture.</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neutral</td><td align="left">No significant impact on food security or agricultural sustainability.</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Violate</td><td align="left">Reduces food security or agricultural productivity through unsustainable practices.</td><td align="left">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly violate</td><td align="left">Causes severe harm to food systems and food security.</td><td align="left">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">SDG 3 (good health and well-being)</td><td align="left">Strongly fulfill</td><td align="left">Directly improves health outcomes, enhances sanitation, and supports disease prevention.</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fulfill</td><td align="left">Indirectly supports health and well-being by improving safety, hygiene, or environmental quality.</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neutral</td><td align="left">No significant impact on public health or well-being.</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Violate</td><td align="left">Contributes to poor health outcomes through pollution or exposure to harmful chemicals.</td><td align="left">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly violate</td><td align="left">Causes severe harm to public health through illegal or unethical practices.</td><td align="left">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">SDG 4 (quality education)</td><td align="left">Strongly fulfill</td><td align="left">Directly enhances educational access, quality, and safety.</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fulfill</td><td align="left">Indirectly supports education by improving safety or access to resources.</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neutral</td><td align="left">No significant impact on education or learning environments.</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Violate</td><td align="left">Negatively impacts educational outcomes through health risks or poor learning environments.</td><td align="left">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly violate</td><td align="left">Severely harms educational systems or access to learning.</td><td align="left">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">SDG 5 (gender equality)</td><td align="left">Strongly fulfill</td><td align="left">Actively promotes gender equality and addresses gender-specific health/safety needs.</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fulfill</td><td align="left">Indirectly supports gender equality through general improvements.</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neutral</td><td align="left">No direct effect on gender equality.</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Violate</td><td align="left">Unintentionally contributes to gender inequality through disproportionate impacts.</td><td align="left">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly violate</td><td align="left">Actively perpetuates gender inequality or creates unsafe environments for women.</td><td align="left">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">SDG 6 (clean water and sanitation)</td><td align="left">Strongly fulfill</td><td align="left">Enhances water quality, sanitation, and sustainable management.</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fulfill</td><td align="left">Positively contributes to water and sanitation without targeted focus.</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neutral</td><td align="left">No significant positive or negative impact on water and sanitation.</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Violate</td><td align="left">Unintentionally harms water quality or sanitation through pollution.</td><td align="left">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly violate</td><td align="left">Actively and severely contaminates water sources.</td><td align="left">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">SDG 7 (affordable and clean energy)</td><td align="left">Strongly fulfill</td><td align="left">Supports the development of clean, sustainable, and affordable energy.</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fulfill</td><td align="left">Contributes to energy systems but not fully renewable or clean.</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neutral</td><td align="left">No direct impact on energy sustainability.</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Violate</td><td align="left">Harms energy sustainability through reliance on non-renewable resources.</td><td align="left">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly violate</td><td align="left">Undermines clean energy efforts through environmental harm.</td><td align="left">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">SDG 8 (decent work and economic growth)</td><td align="left">Strongly fulfill</td><td align="left">Promotes sustainable economic growth, job creation, and decent working conditions.</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fulfill</td><td align="left">Positively contributes to economic growth and job creation.</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neutral</td><td align="left">No significant impact on employment or economic growth.</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Violate</td><td align="left">Undermines worker safety or long-term economic sustainability.</td><td align="left">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly violate</td><td align="left">Harms both worker safety and economic sustainability.</td><td align="left">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">SDG 9 (industry, innovation, and infrastructure)</td><td align="left">Strongly fulfill</td><td align="left">Promotes industrial innovation, sustainable infrastructure, and resilient processes.</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fulfill</td><td align="left">Contributes to industrial growth and infrastructure development.</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neutral</td><td align="left">No significant impact on industrialization or innovation.</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Violate</td><td align="left">Hinders sustainable industrial growth and infrastructure.</td><td align="left">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly violate</td><td align="left">Actively harms industrialization and innovation.</td><td align="left">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">SDG 10 (reduced inequalities)</td><td align="left">Strongly fulfill</td><td align="left">Directly reduces inequalities by improving access to resources.</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fulfill</td><td align="left">Indirectly contributes to reducing inequalities.</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neutral</td><td align="left">No direct impact on inequality.</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Violate</td><td align="left">Contributes to inequality by creating barriers or exacerbating disparities.</td><td align="left">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly violate</td><td align="left">Severely worsens inequality.</td><td align="left">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">SDG 11 (sustainable cities and communities)</td><td align="left">Strongly fulfill</td><td align="left">Directly contributes to sustainable, resilient, and inclusive urban development.</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fulfill</td><td align="left">Supports urban sustainability through efficiency or resource use.</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neutral</td><td align="left">No impact on urban sustainability.</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Violate</td><td align="left">Negatively impacts urban environments.</td><td align="left">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly violate</td><td align="left">Severely harms urban sustainability and safety.</td><td align="left">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">SDG 12 (responsible consumption and production)</td><td align="left">Strongly fulfill</td><td align="left">Drives sustainable consumption and production, promoting resource efficiency.</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fulfill</td><td align="left">Contributes to sustainable production by improving efficiency.</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neutral</td><td align="left">No significant impact on responsible consumption and production.</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Violate</td><td align="left">Leads to unsustainable consumption or production practices.</td><td align="left">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly violate</td><td align="left">Actively undermines responsible consumption and production.</td><td align="left">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">SDG 13 (climate action)</td><td align="left">Strongly fulfill</td><td align="left">Supports climate action through low-emission processes and carbon reduction.</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fulfill</td><td align="left">Contributes to climate mitigation or adaptation.</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neutral</td><td align="left">No direct impact on climate action.</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Violate</td><td align="left">Increases greenhouse gas emissions or hinders climate mitigation.</td><td align="left">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly violate</td><td align="left">Actively worsens climate change through high emissions.</td><td align="left">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">SDG 14 (life below water)</td><td align="left">Strongly fulfill</td><td align="left">Protects marine ecosystems and prevents water pollution.</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fulfill</td><td align="left">Indirectly supports marine life by reducing pollution.</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neutral</td><td align="left">No significant impact on marine ecosystems.</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Violate</td><td align="left">Harms marine life through pollution or habitat destruction.</td><td align="left">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly violate</td><td align="left">Causes severe damage to marine ecosystems.</td><td align="left">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">SDG 15 (life on land)</td><td align="left">Strongly fulfill</td><td align="left">Enhances terrestrial ecosystems and biodiversity.</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fulfill</td><td align="left">Supports terrestrial sustainability through reduced impact.</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neutral</td><td align="left">No direct impact on terrestrial ecosystems.</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Violate</td><td align="left">Degrades land quality or harms biodiversity.</td><td align="left">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly violate</td><td align="left">Severely damages ecosystems and biodiversity.</td><td align="left">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">SDG 16 (peace, justice, and strong institutions)</td><td align="left">Strongly fulfill</td><td align="left">Promotes justice, safety, and ethical practices.</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fulfill</td><td align="left">Indirectly supports peace and justice through ethical practices.</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neutral</td><td align="left">No direct impact on peace, justice, or institutional strength.</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Violate</td><td align="left">Contributes to environmental injustice or conflict.</td><td align="left">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly violate</td><td align="left">Actively threatens peace, justice, or security.</td><td align="left">-2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">SDG 17 (partnerships for the goals)</td><td align="left">Strongly fulfill</td><td align="left">Enhances global partnerships and capacity-building.</td><td align="left">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fulfill</td><td align="left">Supports partnerships through shared resources or knowledge.</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Neutral</td><td align="left">No direct impact on partnerships or capacity-building.</td><td align="left">0</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Violate</td><td align="left">Limits global partnerships or exacerbates disparities.</td><td align="left">-1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Strongly violate</td><td align="left">Hinders international cooperation and progress.</td><td align="left">-2</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par14">
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Visualization of four hypothetical sustainability performance scenarios assessed using the SUSTAIN metric. (<bold>a</bold>) Optimal scenario with full achievement of all 17 SDGs (all green radials); (<bold>b</bold>) Suboptimal yet acceptable scenario with mixed fulfillment levels (<bold>c</bold>) Neutral scenario with a total score of zero, indicating equal support and violation of SDGs; (<bold>d</bold>) Negative scenario where the initiative demonstrates a net adverse impact on SDGs.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_23521_Fig1_HTML" id="d33e1004"/></fig>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Results and discussion</title><p id="Par15">To demonstrate the practical application of the SUSTAIN tool, we evaluated three major energy access initiatives active in Africa: Power Africa, Sustainable Energy for All (SE4All), and Climate Finance Initiatives. The assessment covers the documented performance and outcomes of each initiative from its launch until the end of 2023. The scoring is based on evidence drawn from their official progress reports, independent evaluations, and data from affiliated multilateral organizations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>.</p><sec id="Sec7"><title>Case studies</title><p id="Par16">Power Africa<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, SE4All<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup>, and Climate Finance Initiatives<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup> contribute significantly to advancing the SDGs, yet their impacts vary based on their respective approaches and priorities, as illustrated in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>. Power Africa and SE4All strongly support poverty reduction (SDG 1) by increasing energy access, with Climate Finance playing a role primarily through targeted funding mechanisms. In terms of food security (SDG 2), SE4All demonstrates the most substantial impact due to its integrated approach to energy solutions, whereas Power Africa and Climate Finance provide indirect support. All three initiatives contribute positively to health and well-being (SDG 3) by reducing indoor air pollution and improving energy availability for medical facilities. Similarly, their role in promoting quality education (SDG 4) varies, with SE4All making the most significant contributions by explicitly addressing energy needs in educational institutions, while Power Africa and Climate Finance play supportive roles.</p><p id="Par17">Gender equality (SDG 5) is strongly emphasized by SE4All through targeted programs promoting women&#x02019;s participation in the energy sector, whereas Power Africa and Climate Finance include gender considerations but with less explicit focus. Access to clean water and sanitation (SDG 6) benefits from all three initiatives, although Climate Finance has the most substantial impact due to its emphasis on sustainable water projects. As expected, all three initiatives strongly fulfill the goal of providing affordable and clean energy (SDG 7) and contribute to economic growth (SDG 8) by fostering job creation and industrial development. Their support for industry, innovation, and infrastructure (SDG 9) remains substantial, particularly through investments in energy-related infrastructure.</p><p id="Par18">In addressing inequalities (SDG 10), SE4All demonstrates a more direct focus on equitable energy distribution, whereas Power Africa and Climate Finance provide indirect benefits. SE4All and Climate Finance strongly promote sustainable cities and communities (SDG 11), while Power Africa primarily targets rural electrification, resulting in a relatively lower impact on urban sustainability. The initiatives differ significantly in their alignment with responsible consumption and production (SDG 12). Power Africa receives a negative assessment due to its continued support for natural gas and fossil fuel projects, whereas SE4All fosters more sustainable energy consumption, and Climate Finance strongly promotes sustainability.</p><p id="Par19">
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>SUSTAIN scores for Power Africa (<bold>a</bold>), SE4All (<bold>b</bold>) and climate finance (<bold>c</bold>) initiatives.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2025_23521_Fig2_HTML" id="d33e1058"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par20">Climate action (SDG 13) represents another area where Power Africa&#x02019;s fossil fuel investments result in a negative impact despite its contributions to renewable energy development. By contrast, SE4All and Climate Finance prioritize low-carbon energy solutions, aligning more strongly with global climate goals. Regarding biodiversity-related SDGs, Climate Finance has the strongest positive influence on life below water (SDG 14) and life on land (SDG 15) due to its focus on sustainable environmental projects. SE4All demonstrates limited but positive contributions, while Power Africa remains largely neutral in these domains.</p><p id="Par21">Finally, all three initiatives contribute to peace, justice, and strong institutions (SDG 16) by promoting governance and institutional capacity-building. They also play a crucial role in fostering international partnerships for sustainable development (SDG 17), with Power Africa, SE4All, and Climate Finance all relying on cross-sector collaborations and global partnerships to advance their objectives. Based on these findings, it can be concluded that each initiative contributes meaningfully to the SDGs. Moreover, Power Africa&#x02019;s engagement with fossil fuel projects presents limitations in fully aligning with sustainability principles, particularly in climate action and responsible consumption.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Novelty and comparison with existing assessment tools</title><p id="Par22">Several robust frameworks exist for sustainability assessment, each with distinct strengths. Life Cycle Assessment (LCA) and Multi-Criteria Decision Analysis (MCDA) are powerful, data-intensive methods that provide deep, granular insights into environmental impacts or complex trade-offs, respectively<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup>. Similarly, Triple Bottom Line (TBL) indices effectively aggregate environmental, social, and economic performance into a standardized format<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. Furthermore, numerous organizations have developed frameworks for mapping projects to the SDGs, often qualitatively describing synergies and trade-offs.</p><p id="Par23">The SUSTAIN tool builds upon these foundations but introduces key innovations that address the following specific gaps. Unlike many SDG-mapping frameworks that remain qualitative or descriptive, SUSTAIN provides a standardized, quantitative scoring system (-2 to + 2) for each of the 17 SDGs. This transforms the SDGs from a communicative framework into an analytical metric, allowing for direct comparison between diverse initiatives. While LCA is exceptionally detailed, it can be resource-intensive and often focuses predominantly on environmental parameters. SUSTAIN is designed to incorporate social and economic dimensions with the same structural weight as environmental ones, using the SDG framework. It offers a more holistic view than a pure LCA and is less data-intensive, making it suitable for preliminary screening, policy analysis, and comparing initiatives where full-scale LCA is not feasible. Unlike static TBL indices or complex MCDA outputs, SUSTAIN&#x02019;s output includes a dynamic radial diagram (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) that provides an immediate, intuitive visual snapshot of a project&#x02019;s sustainability profile across all 17 goals. This visual synthesis is a key feature for communicating complex assessment results to policymakers, stakeholders, and non-experts. The tool is not limited to a specific sector (e.g., only chemistry or only energy). Its structure, based on the universally accepted SDGs, allows for the comparative assessment of a wide range of initiatives, from industrial processes to large-scale development programs, as demonstrated in the case studies. It is crucial to distinguish between &#x0201c;greenness,&#x0201d; which focuses predominantly on environmental impacts (e.g., pollution, resource use), and &#x0201c;sustainability,&#x0201d; which is a broader, multi-dimensional concept encompassing social, economic, and environmental pillars, as embodied by the 17 SDGs. Consequently, established metrics of greenness, such as modified green start area (MoGSA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>, modified green analytical procedure index (MoGAPI)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref></sup>, analytical green star area (AGSA)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>, and carbon foot print reduction index (CaFRI)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>, green environmental assessment and rating for solvents (GEARS)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref></sup> are inherently limited; they cannot be used to assess the different social and economic SDGs, as they lack the necessary scope. SUSTAIN is designed to fill this gap.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Sensitivity analysis</title><p id="Par24">The assignment of specific weights to each SDG is a critical step in tailoring the SUSTAIN assessment to reflect particular priorities. To test the robustness of the comparative conclusions derived from this weighted framework, a sensitivity analysis was performed using alternative policy-focused weighting scenarios. Three distinct scenarios were constructed, each representing a different strategic priority. An Environmental Weighting scenario assigned double the original weight to SDGs 6, 7, 13, 14, and 15. A Social Weighting scenario applied this same doubling to SDGs 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, and 10. Finally, an Economic/Industrial Weighting scenario doubled the weights for SDGs 8, 9, and 12.</p><p id="Par25">The results of this analysis, detailed in Supplementary Table <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>, demonstrate a high degree of robustness in the SUSTAIN metric&#x02019;s outcomes while also identifying a key point of sensitivity. The relative performance ranking of the initiatives proved robust under both the Environmental and Social weighting scenarios, with the ordinal ranking of SE4All first, followed by Climate Finance Initiatives and then Power Africa remaining unchanged from the default weighting. However, under the Economic/Industrial Weighting scenario, the Climate Finance Initiatives achieved a normalized score of 85.00, drawing equal with SE4All. This shift creates a tie for the top rank and is directly attributable to the high performance of Climate Finance on the up-weighted goals, particularly SDG 12 (Responsible Consumption and Production), where it scored&#x02009;+&#x02009;4 after weighting, compared to Power Africa&#x02019;s score of -2.</p><p id="Par26">This result enhances the SUSTAIN&#x02019;s utility as a diagnostic tool. It reveals that the distinction between the top-performing initiatives is most sensitive to priorities surrounding economic and industrial goals. For stakeholders who prioritize SDGs 8, 9, and 12, the Climate Finance Initiatives represent a sustainability performance on par with SE4All. Conversely, the finding that Power Africa consistently ranked third across all scenarios robustly identifies it as the lower-performing initiative of the three, regardless of the chosen policy priority. This deep understanding of both stability and sensitivity is a key strength of the SUSTAIN assessment.</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Limitations</title><p id="Par27">While the SUSTAIN framework provides a valuable tool for standardized sustainability assessment, several limitations should be acknowledged. The quality of the SUSTAIN assessment is directly dependent on the availability and quality of the underlying data used for the evaluation. In cases where project data is incomplete, outdated, or non-transparent, the accuracy of the score may be compromised. The tool performs best when applied to initiatives with comprehensive and publicly available reporting. The case studies presented focus on large-scale, multi-national energy initiatives in Africa. The tool&#x02019;s applicability to smaller-scale projects, different sectors, or other geographical contexts, while theoretically sound, has not been empirically demonstrated in this work and remains an area for future research. These limitations, however, also present clear pathways for further development and refinement of the SUSTAIN methodology.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par28">This study introduced the Sustainability Universal Scoring and Tracking Application (SUSTAIN), a novel and user-friendly tool designed to provide a quantitative, holistic assessment of sustainability aligned with the United Nations&#x02019; Sustainable Development Goals. The SUSTAIN framework transforms the qualitative SDG framework into a standardized scoring system, enabling the direct comparison of diverse initiatives across environmental, social, and economic dimensions. The tool as available as a user-friendly application at bit.ly/SUSTAIN2025.The application of SUSTAIN to three major energy initiatives in Africa&#x02014;Power Africa, SE4All, and Climate Finance Initiatives&#x02014;successfully demonstrated its utility, yielding distinct scores of 50.00, 85.29, and 82.35, respectively. These results not only provide a clear, comparative benchmark for these programs but also validate SUSTAIN &#x02018;s capacity to identify specific strengths and weaknesses in sustainability performance, such as the trade-offs between energy access and climate action observed in the Power Africa case. Despite its promising applications, the SUSTAIN tool has certain limitations. The tool&#x02019;s effectiveness is dependent on the availability and quality of transparent data from the assessed initiatives. Looking forward, several pathways for future research and tool enhancement are apparent. First, applying SUSTAIN to a wider array of initiatives, including smaller-scale projects and different sectors such as agriculture, manufacturing, and waste management, would further validate its universal applicability. Second, developing a user-friendly offline software would facilitate SUSTAIN applicability. By providing a standardized and intuitive platform for SDG-based assessment, SUSTAIN offers a critical step forward in enabling more transparent, comparable, and data-driven decisions for a sustainable future.</p></sec><sec id="Sec12" sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Information</title><p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.</p><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2025_23521_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><caption><p>Supplementary Material 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author contributions</title><p>Fotouh R. Mansour: conceptualization and supervision, methodology, validation, results interpretation, and writing&#x02014;original draft, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editingAlaa Bedair: methodology, validation, results interpretation, and writing&#x02014;original draft, Writing&#x02014;review &#x00026; editing.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>Open access funding provided by The Science, Technology &#x00026; Innovation Funding Authority (STDF) in cooperation with The Egyptian Knowledge Bank (EKB).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data availability</title><p>Data will be made available upon reasonable request.</p></notes><notes id="FPar1" notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par29">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR1" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kasinathan</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pugazhendhi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Elavarasan</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Realization of sustainable development goals with disruptive technologies by integrating industry 5. 0, society 5. 0, smart cities and villages</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2022</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>15258</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su142215258</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR1" publication-type="journal">Kasinathan, P., Pugazhendhi, R. &#x00026; Elavarasan, R. M. Realization of sustainable development goals with disruptive technologies by integrating industry 5. 0, society 5. 0, smart cities and villages. <italic>Sustainability</italic><bold>14</bold>, 15258 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR2" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Micro) plastics and the UN sustainable development goals</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Green. Sustain. Chem.</source><year>2019</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>100497</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cogsc.2021.100497</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR2" publication-type="journal">Walker, T. R. Micro) plastics and the UN sustainable development goals. <italic>Curr. Opin. Green. Sustain. Chem.</italic><bold>30</bold>, 100497 (2019).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR3" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Biermann</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Scientific evidence on the political impact of the sustainable development goals</article-title><source>Nat. Sustain.</source><year>2022</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>795</fpage><lpage>800</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41893-022-00909-5</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR3" publication-type="journal">Biermann, F. et al. Scientific evidence on the political impact of the sustainable development goals. <italic>Nat. Sustain.</italic><bold>5</bold>, 795&#x02013;800 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR4" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Obaideen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Shehata</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Taha</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of wastewater treatment in achieving sustainable development goals (SDGs) and sustainability guideline</article-title><source>Energy Nexus</source><year>2022</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>100112</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.nexus.2022.100112</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR4" publication-type="journal">Obaideen, K., Shehata, N., Taha, E. &#x00026; Ali, M. The role of wastewater treatment in achieving sustainable development goals (SDGs) and sustainability guideline. <italic>Energy Nexus</italic>. <bold>7</bold>, 100112 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR5" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Halkos</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Where do we stand on the 17 sustainable development goals ? An overview on progress</article-title><source>Econ. Anal. Policy</source><year>2021</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.eap.2021.02.001</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR5" publication-type="journal">Halkos, G. Where do we stand on the 17 sustainable development goals ? An overview on progress. <italic>Econ. Anal. Policy</italic>. <bold>70</bold>, 94&#x02013;122 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR6" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A framework for the implementation of the sustainable development goals in university programmes</article-title><source>J. Clean. Prod.</source><year>2021</year><volume>299</volume><fpage>126915</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2021.126915</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR6" publication-type="journal">Leal, W. et al. A framework for the implementation of the sustainable development goals in university programmes. <italic>J. Clean. Prod.</italic><bold>299</bold>, 126915 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Shayan, N. F., Mohabbati-kalejahi, N. &#x00026; Alavi, S. Sustainable development goals (SDGs) as a framework for corporate social responsibility (CSR). <italic>Sustainability</italic><bold>14</bold>, 1222 (2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR8" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lenzen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Implementing the material footprint to measure progress towards sustainable development goals 8 and 12</article-title><source>Nat. Sustain.</source><year>2022</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>157</fpage><lpage>166</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41893-021-00811-6</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR8" publication-type="journal">Lenzen, M. et al. Implementing the material footprint to measure progress towards sustainable development goals 8 and 12. <italic>Nat. Sustain.</italic><bold>5</bold>, 157&#x02013;166 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR9" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mhlanga</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Artificial intelligence in the industry 4. 0, and its impact on Poverty, Innovation, infrastructure development, and the sustainable development goals</article-title><source>Lessons Emerg. Economies ? Sustainability</source><year>2021</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>5788</fpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR9" publication-type="journal">Mhlanga, D. Artificial intelligence in the industry 4. 0, and its impact on Poverty, Innovation, infrastructure development, and the sustainable development goals. <italic>Lessons Emerg. Econom. Sustain.</italic><bold>13</bold>, 5788 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR10" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Falcone</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hiete</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sapio</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hydrogen economy and sustainable development goals: review and policy insights</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Green. Sustain. Chem.</source><year>2021</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>100506</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cogsc.2021.100506</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR10" publication-type="journal">Falcone, P. M., Hiete, M. &#x00026; Sapio, A. Hydrogen economy and sustainable development goals: review and policy insights. <italic>Curr. Opin. Green. Sustain. Chem.</italic><bold>31</bold>, 100506 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR11" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henderson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Loreau</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A model of sustainable development goals: challenges and opportunities in promoting human well-being and environmental sustainability</article-title><source>Ecol. Model. J.</source><year>2023</year><volume>475</volume><fpage>110164</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2022.110164</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR11" publication-type="journal">Henderson, K. &#x00026; Loreau, M. A model of sustainable development goals: challenges and opportunities in promoting human well-being and environmental sustainability. <italic>Ecol. Model. J.</italic><bold>475</bold>, 110164 (2023).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR12" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khaled</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohamed</surname><given-names>EK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A. The sustainable development goals and corporate sustainability performance: Mapping, extent and determinants</article-title><source>J. Clean. Prod.</source><year>2021</year><volume>311</volume><fpage>127599</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2021.127599</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR12" publication-type="journal">Khaled, R., Ali, H. &#x00026; Mohamed, E. K. A. The sustainable development goals and corporate sustainability performance: Mapping, extent and determinants. <italic>J. Clean. Prod.</italic><bold>311</bold>, 127599 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR13" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allela</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A 2020 desk review of power Africa</article-title><source>J. Int. Dev.</source><year>2022</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>334</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jid.3595</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR13" publication-type="journal">Allela, T. A 2020 desk review of power Africa. <italic>J. Int. Dev.</italic><bold>34</bold>, 334&#x02013;348 (2022).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR14" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chirambo</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards the achievement of SDG 7 in sub-Saharan africa: creating synergies between power Africa, sustainable energy for all and climate finance in-order to achieve universal energy access before 2030</article-title><source>Renew. Sustain. Energy Rev.</source><year>2018</year><volume>94</volume><fpage>600</fpage><lpage>608</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.rser.2018.06.025</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR14" publication-type="journal">Chirambo, D. Towards the achievement of SDG 7 in sub-Saharan africa: creating synergies between power Africa, sustainable energy for all and climate finance in-order to achieve universal energy access before 2030. <italic>Renew. Sustain. Energy Rev.</italic><bold>94</bold>, 600&#x02013;608 (2018).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Michaelowa, A. A vision for international climate finance after 2025. In <italic>Handbook of International Climate Finance</italic> (eds Michaelowa, A. &#x00026; Sacherer, A. K.) 476&#x02013;486 10.4337/9781784715656.00030. (Edward Elgar Publishing, 2022).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR16" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pryshlakivsky</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Searcy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Life cycle assessment as a decision-making tool: practitioner and managerial considerations</article-title><source>J. Clean. Prod.</source><year>2021</year><volume>309</volume><fpage>127344</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jclepro.2021.127344</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR16" publication-type="journal">Pryshlakivsky, J. &#x00026; Searcy, C. Life cycle assessment as a decision-making tool: practitioner and managerial considerations. <italic>J. Clean. Prod.</italic><bold>309</bold>, 127344 (2021).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR17" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cinelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Coles</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirwan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analysis of the potentials of multi criteria decision analysis methods to conduct sustainability assessment</article-title><source>Ecol. Indic.</source><year>2014</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>138</fpage><lpage>148</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolind.2014.06.011</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR17" publication-type="journal">Cinelli, M., Coles, S. R. &#x00026; Kirwan, K. Analysis of the potentials of multi criteria decision analysis methods to conduct sustainability assessment. <italic>Ecol. Indic.</italic><bold>46</bold>, 138&#x02013;148 (2014).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR18" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Slaper</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The triple bottom line: what is it and how does it work</article-title><source>Indiana Bus. Rev.</source><year>2011</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>4</fpage><lpage>8</lpage></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR18" publication-type="journal">Slaper, T. F. &#x00026; Hall, T. J. The triple bottom line: what is it and how does it work. <italic>Indiana Bus. Rev.</italic><bold>86</bold>, 4&#x02013;8 (2011).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR19" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Hassab</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Majrashi</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Eldehna</surname><given-names>WM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A modified green star area (MoGSA) and software to assess greenness of reactions in the chemistry laboratories</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2024</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>e0314421</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0314421</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 39630641?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39630641</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR19" publication-type="journal">Mansour, F. R., Hassab, E., Majrashi, M. A., Eldehna, W. M. &#x00026; T. A. &#x00026; A modified green star area (MoGSA) and software to assess greenness of reactions in the chemistry laboratories. <italic>PLoS One</italic>. <bold>19</bold>, e0314421 (2024).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">39630641</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Mansour, F. R., P&#x00142;otka-Wasylka, J., Locatelli, M. &#x00026; Modified, G. A. P. I. (MoGAPI) Tool and software for the assessment of method greenness: Case studies and applications. <italic>Analytica</italic><bold>5</bold>, 451&#x02013;457 (2024).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR21" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Omer</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x00142;otka-Wasylka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A total scoring system and software for complex modified GAPI (ComplexMoGAPI) application in the assessment of method greenness</article-title><source>Green. Anal. Chem.</source><year>2024</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>100126</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.greeac.2024.100126</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR21" publication-type="journal">Mansour, F. R., Omer, K. M. &#x00026; P&#x00142;otka-Wasylka, J. A total scoring system and software for complex modified GAPI (ComplexMoGAPI) application in the assessment of method greenness. <italic>Green. Anal. Chem.</italic><bold>10</bold>, 100126 (2024).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR22" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedair</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Belal</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Magdy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Locatelli</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analytical green star area (AGSA) as a new tool to assess greenness of analytical methods</article-title><source>Sustain. Chem. Pharm.</source><year>2025</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>102051</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scp.2025.102051</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR22" publication-type="journal">Mansour, F. R., Bedair, A., Belal, F., Magdy, G. &#x00026; Locatelli, M. Analytical green star area (AGSA) as a new tool to assess greenness of analytical methods. <italic>Sustain. Chem. Pharm.</italic><bold>46</bold>, 102051 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR23" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Nowak</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Introducing the carbon footprint reduction index (CaFRI) as a software-supported tool for greener laboratories in chemical analysis</article-title><source>BMC Chem.</source><year>2025</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>121</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13065-025-01486-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 40346688?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40346688</pub-id>
</element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR23" publication-type="journal">Mansour, F. R. &#x00026; Nowak, P. M. Introducing the carbon footprint reduction index (CaFRI) as a software-supported tool for greener laboratories in chemical analysis. <italic>BMC Chem.</italic><bold>19</bold>, 121 (2025).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">40346688</pub-id>
</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><citation-alternatives><element-citation id="ec-CR24" publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mansour</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedair</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Green environmental assessment and rating for solvents (GEARS) as an innovative tool for solvent selection</article-title><source>Sustain. Chem. Pharm.</source><year>2025</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>102157</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scp.2025.102157</pub-id></element-citation><mixed-citation id="mc-CR24" publication-type="journal">Mansour, F. R. &#x00026; Bedair, A. Green environmental assessment and rating for solvents (GEARS) as an innovative tool for solvent selection. <italic>Sustain. Chem. Pharm.</italic><bold>47</bold>, 102157 (2025).</mixed-citation></citation-alternatives></ref></ref-list></back></article>